<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a book published by Dr. Bramhall, late bishop of Derry; called the Catching of the leviathan. Together with an historical narration concerning heresie, and the punishment thereof. By Thomas Hobbes of Malmesbury</title>
            <author>Hobbes, Thomas, 1588-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43970</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19913</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828707</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828707</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33138</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43970)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33138)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1868:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a book published by Dr. Bramhall, late bishop of Derry; called the Catching of the leviathan. Together with an historical narration concerning heresie, and the punishment thereof. By Thomas Hobbes of Malmesbury</title>
                  <author>Hobbes, Thomas, 1588-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for W. Crooke at the Green Dragon without Temple-Barr,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Bramshall, John.  The catching of the Leviathan, or the great whale.</note>
                  <note>"An historical narration concerning heresie, and the punishment thereof" has separate dated title page. Pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Also isused as part of "Tracts of Mr. Thomas Hobbs of Malmsbury" (Wing (2nd ed.) H2265), 1682.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bramhall, John, 1594-1663. --  Catching of the leviathan, or the great whale --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Heresy --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33138:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO A BOOK Publiſhed by D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>BRAMHALL,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Derry;</hi> CALLED The Catching of the <hi>Leviathan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together With an Hiſtorical Narration Concerning HERESIE, And the Puniſhment thereof.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS HOBBES</hi> of <hi>Malmeſbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Crooke</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Barr,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33138:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33138:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in all things which I have written, ſo alſo in this Piece, I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured all I can to be perſpicuous; but yet your own attention is always neceſſary. The late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Derry</hi> publiſhed a Book called <hi>The Catching of Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> in which he hath put together divers Sentences pickt out of my <hi>Leviathan,</hi> which ſtand there plainly and firmly prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſets them down without their Proofs, and without the order of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance one upon another; and calls them Atheiſm, Blaſphemy, Impiety, Subverſion of Religion, and by other names of that kind. My requeſt unto you is, That when he cites my words for Erroneous, you
<pb facs="tcp:33138:3"/>will be pleaſed to turn to the place it ſelf, and ſee whether they be well proved, and how to be underſtood. Which labour his Lordſhip might have ſaved you, if he would have vouchſafed, as well to have weighed my Arguments before you, as to have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you my Concluſions. His Book contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth two Chapters, the one concerning Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the other concerning Politicks. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he does not ſo much as offer any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of any thing in my <hi>Leviathan</hi> concluded, I needed not to have anſwered either of them. Yet to the firſt I here an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, becauſe the words <hi>Atheiſm, Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety</hi> and the like, are words of the greateſt defamation poſſible. And this I had done ſooner, if I had ſooner known that ſuch a Book was extant. He wrote it ten years ſince, and yet I never heard of it till about three Months ſince; ſo little talk there was of his Lordſhip's Writings. If you want leaſure or care of the queſtions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, I pray you condemn me not upon report. To judge and not examine is not just. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. Hobbes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33138:3"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> That the <hi>Hobbian</hi> Principles are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Chriſtianity and all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J.D.</speaker>
                     <p>THe Image of God is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together defaced by the fall of Man, but that there will remain ſome practical notions of God and Goodneſs; which, when the mind is free from vagrant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and violent paſſions, do ſhine as clearly in the heart, as other ſpeculative notions do in the head. Hence it is, That there was never any Nation ſo barbarous or ſavage throughout the whole world, which had not their God. They who did never wear cloaths upon their backs, who did never know Magiſtrate but their Father, yet have their God, and their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Rites and Devotions to him. Hence it is, That the greateſt Atheiſts in any ſudden danger do unwittingly caſt their eyes up to Heaven, as craving aid from thence, and in a thunder creep into ſome hole to hide themſelves. And they who are conſcious to themſelves of any ſecret Crimes, though they be ſecure
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33138:4"/>enough from the juſtice of men, do yet feel the blind blows of a Guilty Conſcience, and fear Divine Vengeance. This is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by <hi>T. H.</hi> himſelf in his lucid Intervals. <hi>That we may know what worſhip of God natural reaſon doth aſſign, let us begin with his attributes, where it is manifeſt in the firſt place, That exiſtency is to be attributed to him.</hi> To which he addeth <hi>Infiniteneſs, Incomprehenſibility, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquity.</hi> Thus for Attributes, next for Actions. <hi>Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing external Actions, wherewith God is to be worſhipped, the moſt general precept of reaſon is, that they be ſigns of honour,</hi> under which are contained <hi>Prayers, Thankſgivings, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> and <hi>Sacrifices.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Hitherto his Lordſhip diſcharges me of Atheiſme. What need he to ſay that <hi>All Nations, how barbarous ſoever, yet have their Gods and Religious Rites, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts are frighted with thunder, and feel the blind blows of Conſcience?</hi> It might have been as apt a Preface to any other of his Diſcourſes as this. I expect therefore in the next place to be told that I deny a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain my afore recited Doctrine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet to let us ſee how inconſiſtent and irreconcileable he is with himſelf, elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where reckoning up all the Laws of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at large, even twenty in number, he hath not one word that concerneth Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33138:4"/>or that hath the leaſt relation in the world to God. As if a man were like the Colt of a wild Aſſe in the wilderneſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any owner or obligation. Thus in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the Laws of Nature, this great Clerk forgeteth the God of Nature, and the main and principle Laws of Nature, which contains a mans duty to his God, and the principal end of his Creation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>After I had ended the diſcourſe he mentions of the Laws of Nature, I thought it fitteſt in the laſt place once for all, to ſay they were the Laws of God, then when they were delivered in the Word of God; but before being not known by men for any thing but their own natural reaſon, they were but Theorems, tending to peace, and thoſe uncertain, as being but concluſions of particular men, and therefore not properly Laws. Beſides, I had formerly in my Book <hi>De Cive, cap.</hi> 4. proved them ſeverally one by one out of the Scriptures; which his Lordſhip had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ead and knew. 'Twas therefore an unjuſt charge of his to ſay, I had not one word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n them that concerns Religion, or that hath the leaſt relation in the world to God; and this upon no other ground then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat I added not to every article, <hi>This Law <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> in the Scripture.</hi> But why he ſhould call me (ironically) a great Clerk, I cannot
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33138:5"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:33138:5"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:33138:6"/>tell. I ſuppoſe he would make men believe I arrogated to my ſelf all the learning of a great Clerk, Biſhop, or other inferior Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. A Learned Biſhop, is that Biſhop that can interpret all parts of Scripture tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and congruently to the harmony of the whole; that has learnt the Hiſtory and Laws of the Church, down from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time to his own; and knows what is the nature of a Law Civil, Divine, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, and Poſitive; and how to govern well the Parochial Miniſters of his Dioceſs, ſo that they may both by Doctrine and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample keep the people in the belief of all Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith neceſſary to Salvation, and in obedience to the Laws of their Country. This is a Learned Biſhop. A Learned Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is he that hath learned the way by which men may be drawn from Avarice, Pride, Senſuality, Prophaneſs, Rebellious Principles, and all other vices by eloquent and powerful diſgracing them, both from Scripture and from Reaſon; and can terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy men from vice by diſcreet uttering of the puniſhments denounced againſt wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, and by deducing rationally the dammage they receive by it in the end. In one word, he is a Learned Miniſter that can preach ſuch Sermons as St. <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> preached to the <hi>Antiochians</hi> when he was Presbyter in that City. Could his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33138:6"/>find in my Book that I arrogated to my ſelf the eloquence or wiſdom of St. <hi>Chriſoſtom,</hi> or the ability of governing the Church? 'Tis one thing to know what is to be done, another thing to know how to do it. But his Lordſhip was pleaſed to uſe any artifice to diſgrace me in any kind whatſoever.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Perhaps he will ſay that he hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the Laws of Nature there, only ſo far as may ſerve to the conſtitution or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of a Common-wealth. In good time, let it be ſo. He hath deviſed us a trim Common-wealth, which is founded neither upon Religion towards God, nor Juſtice towards Man; but meerly upon ſelf-intereſt, and ſelf-preſervation. Thoſe raies of heavenly Light, thoſe natural ſeeds of Religion, which God himſelf hath imprinted in the heart of man, are more efficatious towards preſervation of a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; whether we regard the nature of the thing, or the bleſſing of God, then all his <hi>Pacts,</hi> and <hi>Surrenders,</hi> and <hi>Tranſlations of power.</hi> He who unteacheth men their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to God, may make them Eye-ſervants, ſo long as their intereſt doth oblige them to obey; but is no fit Maſter to teach men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and fidelity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>He has not yet found the place where I contradict either the Exiſtence,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33138:7"/>or Infiniteneſs, or Incomprehenſibility, or Unity, or Ubiquity of God. I am there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yet abſolved of Atheiſm. But I am, he ſays, inconſiſtent and irreconcileable with my ſelf, that is, I am, (though he ſays not ſo, he thinks) a forgetful blockhead. I cannot help that: But my forgetfulneſs appears not here. Even his Lordſhip where he ſays, Thoſe raies of heavenly Light, thoſe ſeeds of Religion, which God himſelf hath imprinted in the heart of man (meaning natural reaſon) are more efficacious to the preſervation of Society, than all the <hi>Pacts, Surrenders,</hi> and <hi>Tranſlat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Power,</hi> had forgotten to except the Old Pact of the Jews, and the New Pact of Chriſtians. But pardoning that, did he hope to make any wiſe man believe, that when this Nation very lately was an Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and diſſolute multitude of men, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every one what his own reaſon or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed Light ſuggeſted, did again out of that ſame Light call in the King, and piece again, and ask pardon for the faults, which that their illumination had brought them into, rather than out of fear of perpetual danger, and hope of preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Without Religion, Societies are like but ſoapy bubbles, quickly diſſolved. It was the judgment of as wiſe a man
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33138:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>as <hi>T. H.</hi> himſelf (though perhaps he will hardly be perſwaded to it) that <hi>Rome</hi> ought more of its grandeur to Religion, than either to ſtrength or ſtratagems. <hi>We have not exceeded the</hi> Spaniards <hi>in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, nor the</hi> Galls <hi>in ſtrength, nor the</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginians <hi>in craft, nor the</hi> Grecians <hi>in art,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but we have overcome all Nations by our Piety and Religion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Did not his Lordſhip forget him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf here again, in approving this ſentence of <hi>Tully,</hi> which makes the Idolatry of the <hi>Romans,</hi> not only better than the Idolatry of other Nations; but alſo better than the Religion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> whoſe Law Chriſt himſelf ſays, he came not to deſtroy but to fulfil? And that the <hi>Romans</hi> overcame both them and other Nations, by their Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, when it is manifeſt that the <hi>Romans</hi> overran the world by injuſtice and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, and that their Victories ought not to be aſcribed to the Piety of the <hi>Romans,</hi> but to the impiety as well of the <hi>Jews</hi> as of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations? But what meant he by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Tully</hi> was as wiſe a man as <hi>T. H.</hi> himſelf, though perhaps he will hardly be perſwaded to it? Was that any part of the controverſie? No: Then it was out of his way. God promiſeth to aſſiſt good men in their way, but not out of their way. 'Tis therefore the leſs wonder that his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33138:8"/>Lordſhip was in this place deſerted of the Light which God imprints in the hearts of rudeſt Savages.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Among his Laws he incerteth <hi>gratitude</hi> to men as the third precept of the Law of Nature; but of the gratitude of mankind to their Creator, there is a deep ſilence. If men had ſprung up from the earth in a night like Muſhroms or Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſences, without all ſence of Honour, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Conſcience, or Gratitude, he could not have vilified the humane nature more then he doth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord diſcovers here an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſuch method as is neceſſary for lawful and ſtrict reaſoning and explication of the truth in controverſie. And not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that, but alſo how little able he is to fix his mind upon what he reads in other mens Writings. When I had defined Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude univerſally, he finds fault that I do not mention Ingratitude towards God, as if his Lordſhip knew not that an univerſal comprehends all the particulars. When I had defined Equity univerſally, why did he not as well blame me for not telling what that Equity is in God? He is grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the man of whom he receives a good turn, that confeſſeth or maketh appear he is pleaſed with the benefit he receiveth. So alſo Gratitude towards God is to confeſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33138:8"/>his benefits. There is alſo in Gratitude to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men a deſire to requite their Benefits, ſo there is in our Gratitude towards God, ſo far to requite them, as to be kind to Gods Miniſters, which I acknowledged in make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sacrifices a part of natural Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and the benefit of thoſe Sacrifices is the nouriſhment of Gods Miniſters. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears therefore that the Biſhops attention in reading my Writings was either weak in it ſelf, or weakned by prejudice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>From this ſhameful omiſſion or preterition of the main duty of mankind, a man might eaſily take the height of <hi>T. H.</hi> his Religion. But he himſelf put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it paſt all conjectures. His princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are brim full of prodigious impiety. <hi>In theſe four things, Opinions of Ghoſts, Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſecond Cauſes, devotion to what men fear, and taking of things caſual, for Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticks, conſiſteth the natural ſeed of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> the culture and improvement where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he referreth only to <hi>Policy.</hi> Humane and Divine Politicks, are but Politicks. And again, <hi>Mankind hath this from the conſcience of their own weakneſs, and the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of natural events, that the moſt part of men believe that there is an inviſible God, the maker of all viſible things.</hi> And a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he telleth us, That <hi>Superſtition proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from fear without right reaſon, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33138:9"/>Atheiſme from an opinion of reaſon without fear;</hi> making Atheiſme to be more reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able than Superſtition. What is now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of that Divine Worſhip which natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral reaſon did aſſign unto God, the honour of Exiſtence, Infiniteneſs, Incomprehenſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Unity, Ubiquity? What is now become of that Dictate or Precept of reaſon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Prayers, Thankſgivings, Oblations, Sacrifices,</hi> if uncertain Opinions, Ignorance, Fear, Miſtakes, the conſcience of our own weakneſs, and the admiration of natural Events, be the only ſeeds of Religion?</p>
                     <p>He proceedeth further, That <hi>Atheiſme it ſelf, though it be an erronious opinion, and therefore a ſin, yet it ought to be numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſins of imprudence or ignorance.</hi> He addeth, that <hi>an Atheiſt is puniſhed not as a Subject is puniſhed by his King, becauſe he did not obſerve Laws: but as an Enemy, by an Enemy, becauſe he would not accept Laws.</hi> His reaſon is, becauſe <hi>the Atheiſt never ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted his will to the Will of God, whom he never thought to be.</hi> And he concludeth that mans obligation to obey God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from his weakneſs. <hi>Manifeſtum eſt obligationem ad preſtandum ipſi (Deo) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedientiam, incumbere hominibus propter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becilitatem.</hi> Firſt it is impoſſible that ſhould be a ſin of meer ignorance or imprudence, which is directly contrary to the light
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33138:9"/>of natural reaſon. The Laws of nature need no new promulgation, being imprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed naturally by God in the heart of Man. <hi>The Law of nature was written in our hearts by the finger of God, without our aſſent;</hi> or rather <hi>the Law of Nature is the aſſent it ſelf.</hi> Then if Nature dictate to us that there is a God, and that this God is to be worſhipped in ſuch and ſuch manner, it is not poſſible that Atheiſm ſhould be a ſin of meer ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, a Rebellious Subject is ſtill a Subject, <hi>De Jure,</hi> though not, <hi>De Facto,</hi> by right, though not by deed: and ſo the moſt curſed Atheiſt that is, ought by right to be the Subject of God, and ought to be puniſhed not as a juſt Enemy, but as a diſloyal Traytor. Which is confeſſed by himſelf, <hi>This fourth Sin,</hi> (that is, of thoſe who do not by word and deed confeſs one God the Supreme King of Kings) <hi>in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Kingdom of God is the Crime of High Treaſon, for it is a denial of Divine Power, or Atheiſm.</hi> Then an Atheiſt is a Traytor to God, and puniſhable as a diſloyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, not as an Enemy.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, it is an abſurd and diſhonourable aſſertion, to make our obedience to God to depend upon our weakneſs, becauſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help it, and not upon our gratitude, becauſe we owe our being and preſervation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33138:10"/>to him. <hi>Who planteth a Vineyard, and eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not of the Fruit thereof? And who feedeth a Flock, and eateth not of the Milk of the Flock?</hi> And again, <hi>Thou art worthy O Lord to receive Glory, and Honour, and Power, for thou haſt created all things, and for thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they are and were created.</hi> But it were much better or at leaſt not ſo ill, to be a down right Atheiſt, than to make God to be ſuch a thing as he doth, and at laſt thruſt him into the Devils Office, to be the cauſe of all Sin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Though this Biſhop, as I ſaid, had but a weak attention in reading, and little skill in examining the force of an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet he knew men, and the art, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out troubling their judgments to win their aſſents by exciting their Paſſions. One Rule of his art was to give his Reader what he would have him ſwallow, a part by it ſelf, and in the nature of News, whether true or not. Knowing that the unlearned, that is moſt men, are content to believe, rather than be troubled with examining, Therefore (a little before) he put theſe words <hi>T. H. no friend to Religion,</hi> in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. And in this place, before he offer at any confutation, he ſays my Principles are brim full of <hi>Prodigious Impieties.</hi> And at the next Paragraph, in the Margent, he puts that <hi>I excuſe Atheiſm.</hi> This behaviour
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33138:10"/>becomes neither a Biſhop, nor a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, nor any man that pretends to good education. Fear of inviſible powers, what is it elſe in ſavage people, but the fear of ſomewhat they think a God? What invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible power does the reaſon of a ſavage man ſuggeſt unto him, but thoſe Phantaſms of his ſleep, or his diſtemper, which we frequently call Ghoſts, and the Savages thought Gods; ſo that the fear of a God (though not of the true one) to them was the beginning of Religion, as the fear of the true God was the beginning of wiſdom to the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians?</hi> Ignorance of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſes made men fly to ſome firſt cauſe, the fear of which bred Devotion and Worſhip. The ignorance of what that power might do, made them obſerve the order of what he had done; that they might gueſs by the like order, what he was to do another time. This was their Prognoſtication. What Prodigious impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is here? How confutes he it? Muſt it be taken for Impiety upon his bare calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny? I ſaid Superſtition was fear without reaſon. Is not the fear of a falſe God, or fancied Daemon contrary to right reaſon? And is not Atheiſm Boldneſs grounded on falſe reaſoning, ſuch as is this, <hi>the wicked proſper, therefore there is no God?</hi> He offers no proof againſt any of this; but ſays only
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33138:11"/>I make Atheiſm to be more reaſonable than Superſtition; which is not true: For I deny that there is any reaſon either in the Atheiſt or in the Superſtitious. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Atheiſt thinks he has reaſon, where he has none, I think him the more irrational of the two. But all this while he argues not againſt any of this; but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires only, what is become of my natural Worſhip of God, and of his Exiſtency, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finiteneſs, Incomprehenſibility, Unity, and Ubiquity. As if whatſoever reaſon can ſuggeſt, muſt be ſuggeſted all at once. Firſt, all men by nature had an opinion of Gods Exiſtency, but of his other Attributes not ſo ſoon, but by reaſoning, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. And for the Attributes of the true God, they were never ſuggeſted but by the Word of God written. In that I ſay A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm is a ſin of ignorance, he ſays I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe it. The Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſays, <hi>The fool hath ſaid in his heart, There is no God.</hi> Is it not then a ſin of folly? 'Tis agreed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us, that right reaſon dictates, There is a God. Does it not follow, that deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God is a ſin proceeding from miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſoning. If it be not a ſin of ignorance, it muſt be a ſin of malice. Can a man malice that which he thinks has no being? But may not one think there is a God, and yet maliciouſly deny him? If he think
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33138:11"/>there is a God, he is no Atheiſt; and ſo the queſtion is changed into this, whether any man that thinks there is a God, dares deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berately deny it? For my part I think not. For upon what confidence dares any man (deliberately I ſay) oppoſe the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent? <hi>David</hi> ſaith of himſelf, <hi>My feet were ready to ſlip when I ſaw the proſperity of the wicked.</hi> Therefore it is likely the feet of men leſs holy ſlip oftner. But I think no man living is ſo daring, being out of paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as to hold it as his opinion. Thoſe wicked men that for a long time proceeded ſo ſuccesfully in the late horrid Rebellion, may perhaps make ſome think they were conſtant and reſolved Atheiſts, but I think rather that they forgot God, than believed there was none. He that believes there is ſuch an Atheiſt, comes a little too near that opinion himſelf, Nevertheleſs, if words ſpoken in paſſion ſignifie a denial of a God, no puniſhment praeordained by Law, can be too great for ſuch an inſolence; becauſe there is no living in a Common-wealth with men, to whoſe oaths we cannot rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably give credit. As to that I ſay, <hi>An Atheiſt is puniſhed by God not as a Subject by his King, but as an Enemy, and to my argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for it, namely, becauſe he never acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged himſelf Gods Subject,</hi> He oppoſeth, That if nature dictate that there is a God,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33138:12"/>and to be worſhiped in ſuch and ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, then Atheiſm is not a ſin of meer ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance; as if either I or he did hold that Nature dictates the manner of Gods Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or any article of our Creed, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to worſhip with or without a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice. Secondly, he anſwers that a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel is ſtill a Subject <hi>de Jure,</hi> though not <hi>de Facto:</hi> And 'tis granted. But though the King loſe none of his right by the Traytors act, yet the Traytor loſeth the priviledg of being puniſht by a praecedent Law; and therefore may be puniſh'd at the Kings will, as <hi>Ravillac</hi> was for mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th. of <hi>France.</hi> An open Enemy and a perfidious Traytor are both enemies. Had not his Lordſhip read in the Roman ſtory how <hi>Perſeus</hi> and other juſt enemies of that State were wont to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed? But what is this trifling queſtion to my <hi>excuſing of Atheiſm?</hi> In the ſeventh Paragraph of my Book <hi>de Cive</hi> he found the words (in Latin) which he here citeth. And to the ſame ſenſe I have ſaid in my <hi>Leviathan,</hi> That the right of nature whereby God raigneth over men, is to be derived not from his creating them, as if he required obedience, as of Gratitude; but from his irreſiſtable Power. This he ſays is abſurd and diſhonourable. Whereas firſt all power is honourable, and greateſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33138:12"/>power is moſt honourable. It is not a more noble tenure for a King to hold his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the right to puniſh thoſe that tranſgreſs his Laws from his Power, than from the gratitude or gift of the Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor. There is nothing therefore here of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to God Almighty. But ſee the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tility of his diſputing. He ſaw he could not catch <hi>Leviathan</hi> in this place, he looks for him in my Book <hi>de Cive,</hi> which is Latine, to try what he could fiſh out of that. And ſays I make our obedience to God, depend upon our weakneſs, as if theſe words ſignified the <hi>Dependence,</hi> and not the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of our ſubmiſſion, or that <hi>incumbere</hi> and <hi>dependere</hi> were all one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>For <hi>T. H.</hi> his God is not the God of Chriſtians, nor of any rational men. Our God is every where, and ſeeing he hath no parts, he muſt be wholly here, and wholly there, and wholly every where. So Nature it ſelf dictateth. <hi>It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid honourably of God that he is in a place; for nothing is in a place, but that which hath proper bounds of its greatneſs.</hi> But <hi>T. H.</hi> his God is not wholly every where. <hi>No man can conceive that any thing is all in this place, and all in another place at the ſame time, for none of theſe things ever have or can be incident to ſenſe.</hi> So far well, if by conceiving he mean comprehending; but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33138:13"/>then follows, <hi>That theſe are abſurd Speeches taken upon credit, without any ſignification at all, from deceived Philoſophers, and deceived or deceiving School-men.</hi> Thus he denieth the Ubiquity of God. A Circumſcriptive, a Definitive, and a Repletive being in a place, is ſome heathen language to him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Though I believe the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of God, and that he can do what he will, yet I dare not ſay how every thing is done, becauſe I cannot conceive nor comprehend either the Divine ſubſtance, or the way of its operation. And I think it Impiety to ſpeak concerning God any thing of my own head, or upon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Philoſophers or School-men, which I underſtand not, without warrant in the Scripture: And what I ſay of Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence, I ſay alſo of Ubiquity. But his Lordſhip is more valiant in this place, telling us that God is <hi>wholly here,</hi> and <hi>wholly there,</hi> and <hi>wholly every where;</hi> becauſe he has no parts. I cannot comprehend nor conceive this. For methinks it implies alſo that the whole World is alſo in the whole God, and in every part of God, nor can I conceive how any thing can be called <hi>Whole,</hi> which has no parts, nor can I find any thing of this in the Scripture. If I could find it there, I could believe it; and if I could find it in the publick Doctrine of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33138:13"/>the Church, I could eaſily abſtain from contradicting it. The School-men ſay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that the Soul of Man (meaning his up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Soul, which they call the rational Soul) is alſo <hi>wholly</hi> in <hi>the whole man,</hi> and wholly in every part of the man. What is this but to make the humane Soul the ſame thing in reſpect of mans Body, that God is in reſpect of the World? Theſe his Lordſhip calls here rational men, and ſome of them which applaud this Doctrine, would have the High Court of Parliament corroborate ſuch Doctrines with a Law. I ſaid in my <hi>Leviathan,</hi> that it is no honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable attribute to God, to ſay he is <hi>in a place,</hi> becauſe, infinite is not confined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a place. To which he replies, <hi>T. H. his God is not wholly every where.</hi> I confeſs, the conſequence. For I underſtand in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> he that ſays any thing to be <hi>all here,</hi> means that <hi>neither all nor any of the ſame thing is elſe where.</hi> He ſays further, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ake a <hi>Circumſcriptive, a Definitive, and a Repletive</hi> being in a place to be Heathen Language. Truly, if this Diſpute were at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Bar, I ſhould go near to crave the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtance of the Court, leſt ſome trick might be put upon me in ſuch obſcurity. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or though I know what theſe Latin words ſingly ſignifie, yet I underſtand not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ow any thing is in a <hi>Place Definitively</hi>
                        <pb n="20" facs="tcp:33138:14"/>and not <hi>Circumſcriptively.</hi> For <hi>Definitively</hi> comes from <hi>definio</hi> which is to ſet bounds. And therefore to be in a Place Definitively, is when the bounds of the <hi>place</hi> are every way marked out. But to be in a place Circumſcriptively, is when the bounds of the place are deſcribed round about. To be in a Place Repletive, is to fill a place. Who does not ſee that this dictinction is Canting and Fraud? If any man will call it Pious Fraud, he is to prove the Piety as clearly as I have here explained the Fraud. Beſides, no Fraud can be Pious in any man, but him that hath a lawful Right to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern him whom he beguileth; whom the Biſhop pretends to govern, I cannot tell. Beſides his Lordſhip ought to have conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that every Biſhop is one of the Great Councel, truſted by the King to give their advice with the Lords Temporal, for the making of good Laws, Civil and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical, and not to offer them ſuch obſcure Doctrines, as if, becauſe they are not verſed in School-divinity, therefore they had no Learning at all, nor underſtood the Engliſh Tongue. Why did the Divines of <hi>England</hi> contend ſo much heretofore to have the Bible tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> if they never meant any but themſelves ſhould read it? If a Lay-man be publickly encouraged to ſearch the Scriptures for his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33138:14"/>own Salvation, what has a Divine to do to impoſe upon him any ſtrange inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, unleſs if he make him err to Damnation, he will be damned in his ſtead?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Our God is immutable without any ſhadow of turning by change, to whom all things are preſent, nothing paſt, nothing to come. But <hi>T. H.</hi> his God is meaſured by time, loſing ſomthing that is paſt, and acquiring ſomthing that doth come every minute. That is as much as to ſay, That our God is infinite, and his God is finite, for unto that which is actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally infinite, nothing can be added neither time nor parts. Hear himſelf, <hi>Nor do I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what derogation it can be to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine perfection, to attribute to it Potentiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that is in Engliſh, Power</hi> (ſo little doth he underſtand what Potentiality is) <hi>and ſucceſſive duration.</hi> And he chargeth it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us as a fault; that will not have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to be an <hi>endleſs ſucceſſion of time.</hi> How, <hi>ſucceſſive duration,</hi> and <hi>an endleſs ſucceſſion of time in God?</hi> Then God is infinite, then God is elder to day than he was yeſterday. Away with Blaſphemies. Before he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the Ubiquity of God, and now he deſtroyeth his Eternity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall omit both here and hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth his preambulatory, impertinent, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33138:15"/>uncivil calumnies. The thing he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to prove is this. That it is a deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Divine Power to attribute to it Potentiality (that is in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Power) and Succeſſive Duration. One of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons is, God is infinite, and nothing can be added to infinite, neither of time nor of parts: It is true. And therefore I ſaid, God is infinite and eternal, without begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or end, either of Time or Place; which he has not here confuted, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. He denies Potentiality and Power to be all one, and ſays I little underſtand what Potentiality is. He ought therefore in this place to have defined what Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality is: For I underſtand it to be the ſame with <hi>Potentia,</hi> which is in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Power. There is no ſuch word as Potentiality in the Scriptures, nor in any Author of the Latin Tongue. It is found only in School-Divinity, as a word of Art, or rather as a word of Craft, to amaze and puzzle the Laity. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I no ſooner read than intepreted it. In the next place he ſays, as wondring, How an endleſs ſucceſſion of time in God! Why not? <hi>Gods mercy endureth for ever,</hi> and ſurely God endureth as long as his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, therefore there is duration in God, and conſequently endleſs ſucceſſion of time. <hi>God who in ſundry times and divers manners ſpake in time paſt,</hi> &amp;c. But in a former
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33138:15"/>diſpute with me about Free-will, he hath defined Eternity to be <hi>Nuno ſtans,</hi> that is an <hi>ever ſtanding now,</hi> or <hi>everlaſting inſtant.</hi> This he thinks himſelf bound in honour to defend. What reaſonable ſoul can digeſt this? We read in Scripture, that a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years with God, is but as yeſterday. And why? but becauſe he ſees as clearly to the end of a thouſand years, as to the end of a day. But his Lordſhip affirms, That both a thouſand years and a day are but one inſtant, the ſame <hi>ſtanding Now,</hi> or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. If he had ſhewed an holy Text for this Doctrine, or any Text of the Book of <hi>Common Prayer</hi> (in the Scripture and Book of <hi>Common Prayer</hi> is contained all our Religion) I had yielded to him, but School-Divinity I value little or nothing at all. Though in this he contradict alſo the School-men, who ſay the Soul is eternal only <hi>à parte poſt,</hi> but God is eternal both <hi>à parte poſt,</hi> and <hi>à parte ante.</hi> Thus there are parts in eternity, and eternity being, as his Lordſhip ſays, the divine ſubſtance, the divine ſubſtance has parts, and <hi>Nunc ſtans</hi> has parts. Is not this darkneſs? I take it to be the Kingdom of Darkneſs, and the teachers of it, eſpecially of this Doctrine. That God who is not only <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus,</hi> but alſo <hi>Maximus</hi> is no greater than to be wholly contained in the leaſt Atome
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33138:16"/>of earth, or other body, and that his whole duration is but an inſtant of time, to be either groſly ignorant or ungodly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Our God is a perfect, pure, ſimple indiviſible, infinite Eſſence; free from all compoſition of matter and form, of ſubſtance and accidents. All matter is finite, and he who acteth by his infinite Eſſence, needeth neither Organs, nor Faculties <hi>(id eſt, no pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, note that)</hi> nor accidents, to render him more compleat. But <hi>T. H.</hi> his God is a diviſible God, a compounded God, that hath matter, or qualities, or accidents. Hear himſelf. I argue thus, <hi>The divine ſubſtance is indiviſible, but eternity is the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſubſtance. The Major is evident, becauſe God is</hi> Actus ſimpliciſſimus; <hi>the Minor is confeſſed by all men, that whatſoever is attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God, is God.</hi> Now liſten to his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>The Major is ſo far from being evident, that</hi> Actus ſimpliciſſimus <hi>ſignifieth nothing. The Minor is ſaid by ſome men, thought by no man, whatſoever is thought is underſtood.</hi> The Major was this, <hi>The divine ſubſtance is indiviſible.</hi> Is this far from being evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent? Either it is indiviſible or diviſible. If it be not indiviſible, then it is diviſible, then it is materiate, then it is corporeal, then it hath parts, then it is finite by his own confeſſion. <hi>Habere partes, aut eſſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33138:16"/>totum aliquid, ſunt attributa finitorum.</hi> Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ſilly conceit he chargeth me for ſaying, That <hi>God is not juſt,</hi> but juſtice it ſelf; not eternal, but eternity it ſelf; which he calleth <hi>unſeemly words to be ſaid of God.</hi> And he thinketh he doth me a great courteſie in not adding <hi>Blaſphemous and Atheiſtical.</hi> But his Bolts are ſo ſoon ſhot, and his Reaſons are ſuch vain Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and ſuch drowſie Phantaſies, that no ſad man doth much regard them. Thus he hath already deſtroyed the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biquity, the Eternity, and the Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of God. I wiſh he had conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed better with himſelf, before he had deſperately caſt himſelf upon theſe Rocks.</p>
                     <p>But <hi>paulo majora canamus,</hi> my next charge is, That he deſtroys the very being of God, and leaves nothing in his place, but an empty name. For by taking away all incorporeal ſubſtances, he taketh away God himſelf. The very name (ſaith he) of an incorporeal ſubſtance, is a <hi>Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> And <hi>to ſay that an Angel or Spirit, is an incorporeal ſubſtance, is to ſay in effect, that there is no Angel or Spirit at all.</hi> By the ſame reaſon to ſay, That God is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporeal ſubſtance, is to ſay there is no God at all. Either God is incorporeal, or he is finite, and conſiſts of parts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently is no God. This, That there is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33138:17"/>no incorporeal ſpirit, is that main root of Atheiſm, from which ſo many leſſer branches are daily ſprouting up.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>God is indeed a Perfect, Pure, Simple, Infinite Subſtance; and his Name incommunicable, that is to ſay, not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible into this and that individual God, in ſuch manner as the name of Man is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible into <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John.</hi> And therefore God is individual; which word amongſt the Greeks is expreſſed by the word Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible. Certain Hereticks in the primitive Church, becauſe ſpecial and individual are called Particulars, maintained that Chriſt was a particular God, differing in number from God the Father. And this was the Doctrine that was condemned for Hereſy in the firſt Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> by theſe words, <hi>God hath no parts.</hi> And yet many of the Latin Fathers in their explications of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, have expounded the word <hi>Conſubſtantial,</hi> by the community of nature, which different Species have in their Genus, and different individuals in the Species, as if <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> were <hi>Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial,</hi> becauſe they agree in one humane nature; which is contrary (I confeſs) to the meaning of the <hi>Nice</hi> Fathers. But that in a ſubſtance infinitely great, it ſhould be impoſſible to conſider any thing as not infinite. I do not ſee it there condemned.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33138:17"/>For certainly he that thinks God is in every part of the Church, does not exclude him out of the Church-yard. And is not this a conſidering of him by parts? For di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding a thing which we cannot reach nor ſeparate one part thereof from another, is nothing elſe but conſidering of the ſame by parts. So much concerning Indiviſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity from Natural Reaſon; for I will wade no farther, but relie upon the Scriptures. God is no where ſaid in the Scriptures to be indiviſible, unleſs his Lordſhip meant diviſion, to conſiſt only in ſeparation of parts, which I think he did not. St. <hi>Paul</hi> indeed ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Is Chriſt divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi> Not that the followers of <hi>Paul, Apollo,</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> followed ſome one part, ſome another of Chriſt; but that thinking diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently of his nature, they made as it were different kinds of him. Secondly, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip expounds Simplicity, by not being compounded of Matter and Form, or of Subſtance and Accidents, Unlearnedly. For nothing can be ſo compounded. The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a <hi>Chair</hi> is <hi>Wood,</hi> the form is the figure it hath apt for the intended uſe. Does his Lordſhip think the Chair compounded of the Wood and the Figure? A man is Rational, does it therefore follow that Reaſon is a part of the man? It was <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> deceived him, who had told him
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33138:18"/>that <hi>a Rational living Creature,</hi> is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of a man, and that the definition of a man was his Eſſence; and therefore the Biſhop and other School-men, from this that the word Rational is a part of theſe words <hi>Man is a Rational living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> concluded that the Eſſence of man, was a part of the man, and a <hi>Rational man,</hi> the ſame thing with a Rational Soul. I ſhould wonder how any man, much more a Doctor of Divinity, ſhould be ſo groſly deceived, but that I know naturally the generality of men ſpeak the words of their Maſters by rote, without having any Idea of the things, which the words ſignifie. Laſtly, he calls God an <hi>Eſſence.</hi> If he mean by <hi>Eſſence</hi> the ſame with <hi>Ens,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>I approve it. Otherwiſe, what is <hi>Eſſence?</hi> There is no ſuch word in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Hebrew Language, which has no word anſwerable to the copulative <hi>eſt,</hi> will not bear it. The New Teſtament hath <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, but never for <hi>Eſſence,</hi> nor for <hi>Subſtance,</hi> but only for <hi>Riches.</hi> I come now to his Argument in Mood and Figure, which is this, <hi>The Divine Subſtance is indiviſible.</hi> That's the <hi>Major. Eternity is the Divine Subſtance.</hi> That's the <hi>Minor. Ergo,</hi> the Divine Subſtance is indiviſible. The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, he ſays, is evident, becauſe God is <hi>Actus ſimpliciſſimus.</hi> The Minor is confeſſed,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33138:18"/>he thinks, by all men, becauſe whatſoever is attributed to God, is God. To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that the Major was ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evident, that <hi>Actus Simpliciſſimus</hi> ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing, and that the Minor was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by no man. Firſt, what is <hi>Actus</hi> in the <hi>Major?</hi> does any man underſtand <hi>Actus</hi> for a Subſtance, that is, for a thing ſubſiſting by it ſelf? Is not <hi>Actus</hi> in Engliſh, either an <hi>Act,</hi> or an <hi>Action,</hi> or nothing? or is any of theſe <hi>Subſtances?</hi> If it be evident, why did he not explain <hi>Actus</hi> by a definition? And as to the Minor, though all men in the world underſtand that the <hi>Eternal</hi> is God, yet no man can underſtand that the <hi>Eternity</hi> is God. Perhaps he and the School-men mean by <hi>Actus,</hi> the ſame that they do by <hi>Eſſentia.</hi> What is the <hi>Eſſence</hi> of a <hi>man,</hi> but his <hi>Humanity?</hi> or of <hi>God,</hi> but his <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity;</hi> of <hi>Great,</hi> but <hi>Greatneſs;</hi> and ſo of all other denominating Attributes? And the words God and Deity, are of different ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification. <hi>Damaſcene</hi> a Father of the Church expounding the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies plainly that the <hi>Deity</hi> was incarnate, but all true Chriſtians hold that God was incarnate. Therefore <hi>God</hi> and the Deity, ſignifie divers things; and therefore <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> and <hi>Eternity</hi> are not the ſame, no more than a wiſe man and his wiſdom are the ſame. Nor God and his juſtice the ſame
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33138:19"/>thing, and univerſally 'tis falſe, that the Attribute in the Abſtract is the ſame with the Subſtance, to which it is attributed. Alſo it is univerſally true of God, that the Attribute in the Concrete, and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to which it is attributed, is not the ſame thing. I come now to his next Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod or Paragraph, wherein he would fain prove, that by denying Incorporeal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, I take away Gods Exiſtence. The words he cites here are mine; <hi>To ſay an Angel or Spirit is an Incorporeal Subſtance, is to ſay in effect there is no Angel nor Spirit at all.</hi> It is true alſo, that to ſay that God is an Incorporeal Subſtance, is to ſay in effect there is no God at all. What al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges he againſt it, but the School-Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which I have already anſwered? Scripture he can bring none, becauſe the word Incorporeal is not found in Scripture. But the Biſhop truſting to his Ariſtotelean and Scholaſtick Learning hath hitherto made no uſe of Scripture, ſave only of theſe Texts, <hi>Who hath planted a Vineyard, and eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not of the fruit thereof; or who feedeth a flock, and eateth not of the milk of the flock,</hi> and <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Thou art worthy, O Lord, to receive glory, honour, and power, for thou haſt created all things, and for thy pleaſure they were created;</hi> thereby to prove that the right of God to govern and puniſh mankind
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33138:19"/>is not derived from his Omnipotence. Let us now ſee how he proves Incorporeity by his own Reaſon without Scripture. <hi>Either God</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>is Incorporeal or Finite.</hi> He knows I deny both, and ſay he is <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal</hi> and <hi>Infinite,</hi> againſt which he offers no proof, but only (according to his cuſtom of diſputing) calls it the root of Atheiſm; and interrogates me, what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al thing is left in the world, if God be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporeal, but Body and Accidents? I ſay there is nothing left but Corporeal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. For I have denyed (as he knew) that there is any reality in accidents; and nevertheleſs maintain Gods Exiſtence, and that he is a moſt pure, and moſt ſimple Corporeal Spirit. Here his Lordſhip catching nothing, removes to the eternity of the Trinity, which theſe my grounds (he ſays) deſtroy. How ſo? I ſay the Trinity, and the Perſons thereof are that one pure, ſimple, and eternal Corporeal Spirit; and why does this deſtroy the Trinity, more than if I had called it Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal? He labours here and ſeeketh ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to refreſh himſelf in the word <hi>Perſon,</hi> by the ſame grounds (he ſaith) every King has as many Perſons as there by Juſtices of Peace in his Kingdom, and God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hath as many Perſons as there be Kings, why not? For I never ſaid that all
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33138:20"/>thoſe Kings were that God; and yet God giveth that name to the Kings of the earth. For the ſignification of the word <hi>Perſon,</hi> I ſhall expound it by and by in another place. Here ends his Lordſhips School Argument; now let me come with my Scripture Argument. St. <hi>Paul</hi> concerning Chriſt, (<hi>Col.</hi> 2.9.) ſaith thus, <hi>In him dwelleth all the fullneſs of the Godhead Bodily.</hi> This place <hi>Athanaſius</hi> a great and zealous Doctor in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Councel, and vehement ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of <hi>Arius</hi> the Heretick, who allowed Chriſt to be no otherwiſe God, then as men of excellent piety were ſo called, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth thus. The fullneſs of the Godhead dwelleth in him Bodily (Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>) <hi>id eſt</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>id eſt; Realiter.</hi> So there is one Father for Corporality, and that God was in Chriſt in ſuch manner as Body is in Body. Again, there were in the primitive Church a ſort of Hereticks who maintained that Jeſus Chriſt had not a true real Body, but was onely a Phantaſm or Spright, ſuch as the <hi>Latins</hi> called <hi>Spectra.</hi> Againſt the head of this Sect (whoſe name I think was <hi>Apelles</hi>) <hi>Tertullian</hi> wrote a Book, now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant amongſt his other Works, intituled <hi>De Carne Chriſti,</hi> wherein after he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the nature of Phantaſms, and ſhewed that they had nothing of reality in them, he concludeth with theſe words,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33138:20"/>whatſoever is not <hi>Body,</hi> is <hi>Nothing.</hi> So here is on my ſide a plain Text of Scripture, and two ancient and learned Fathers, nor was this Doctrine of <hi>Tertullian</hi> condemned in the Council of <hi>Nice;</hi> but the diviſion of the Divine Subſtance into God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God the Son, and God the holy Ghoſt. For theſe words, <hi>God has no parts,</hi> were added, for explication of the word <hi>Conſubſtantial,</hi> at the requeſt of the diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fathers, and are farther explained both in <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his Creed, in theſe words, <hi>not three Gods but one God,</hi> and by the conſtant Attribute ever ſince of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual</hi> Trinity. The ſame words never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs do condemn the <hi>Anthropomorphites</hi> alſo: For though there appeared no Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians that profeſſed that God had an Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Body, and conſequently that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were three Individuals, yet the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> were all <hi>Anthropomorphites</hi> and there condemned by thoſe words, <hi>God has no parts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And thus I have anſwered his accuſation concerning the Eternity and Exiſtence of the Divine Subſtance, and made appear that in truth, the queſtion between us, is whether God be a Phantaſme (<hi>id eſt,</hi> an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol of the Fancy, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing) or a Corporeal Spirit, that is to ſay, ſomething that has Magnitude.</p>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:33138:21"/>
                     <p>In this place I think it not amiſs, leaving for a little while this Theological diſpute, to examine the ſignification of thoſe words which have occaſioned ſo much diverſity of opinion in this kind of Doctrine.</p>
                     <p>The word <hi>Subſtance,</hi> in Greek <hi>Hypoſtaſis, Hypoſtan, Hypoſtamenon</hi> ſignifie the ſame thing, namely, a Ground, a Baſe, any thing that has Exiſtence or Subſiſtence <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> any thing that upholdeth that which elſe would fall, in which ſence God is properly the Hypoſtaſis, Baſe, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance that upholdeth all the world, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Subſiſtence not only <hi>in himſelf,</hi> but <hi>from himſelf;</hi> whereas other Subſtances have their ſubſiſtence only in themſelves, not from themſelves. But Metaphorically, Faith is called a Subſtance, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the foundation or Baſe of our Hope; for Faith failing our Hope falls. And 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.4. St. <hi>Paul</hi> having boaſted of the liberal promiſe of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> calls that promiſe the ground, the Hypoſtaſis of that his boaſting. And <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. Chriſt is called the Image of the Subſtance (the Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis) of his Father, and for the proper and adequate ſignification of the word Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſis, the Greek Fathers did always oppoſe it to Apparition or Phantaſme; as when a man ſeeth his face in the water, his real
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33138:21"/>face is called the Hypoſtaſis of the phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick face in the water. So alſo in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the thing underſtood or named, is called Hypoſtaſis, in reſpect of the name, ſo alſo a Body coloured is the Hypoſtaſis, Subſtance and Subject of the colour; and in like manner of all its other Accidents. Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and all other abſtract names are words artificial belonging to the Art of Logick, and ſignifies only the manner how we conſider the Subſtance it ſelf. And of this I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſufficiently in <hi>Pag.</hi> 371.372. of my <hi>Leviathan. Body [Lat.] Corpus [Grae.]</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, is that Subſtance which hath Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude indeterminate, and is the ſame with Corporeal Subſtance; but <hi>A Body</hi> is that which hath Magnitude determinate, and conſequently is underſtood to be <hi>totum</hi> or <hi>integrum aliquid. Pure</hi> and <hi>Simple Body,</hi> is Body of one and the ſame kind, in every part throughout, and if mingled with Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of another kind, though the total be compounded or mixt, the parts neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs retain their ſimplicity, as when water and wine are mixt, the parts of both kinds retain their ſimplicity. For water and wine cannot both be in one and the ſame place at once.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Matter</hi> is the ſame with <hi>Body;</hi> But ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver without reſpect to a Body which is made thereof. <hi>Form</hi> is the aggregate of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33138:22"/>all Accidents together, for which, we give the Matter a new name; ſo <hi>Albedo, whiteneſs</hi> is the Form of <hi>Album,</hi> or <hi>white Body.</hi> So alſo Humanity is the Eſſence of man, and Deity the Eſſence of <hi>Deus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Spirit is Thin, Fluid, Tranſparent, Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Body. The word in Latin ſignifies Breath, Aire, Wind and the like. In Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>from <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Spiro, Flo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I have ſeen, and ſo have many more two waters, one of the River, the other a Mineral Water, ſo like, that no man could diſcern the one from the other by his ſight; yet when they have been both put together, the whole ſubſtance could not by the eye be diſtinguiſhed from milk. Yet we know that the one was not mixt with the other, ſo as every part of the one to be in every part of the other, for that is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, unleſs two Bodies can be in the the ſame place. How then could the change be made in every part, but only by the Activity of the Mineral water, chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it every where to the Senſe, and yet not being every where and in every part of the water? If then ſuch groſs Bodies have ſo great Activity, what ſhall we think of Spirits, whoſe kinds be as many as there be kinds of Liquor, and Activity greater? Can it then be doubted, but that God, who is an infinitely fine Spirit and withall
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33138:22"/>intelligent, can make and change all ſpecies and kinds of Body as he pleaſeth; but I dare not ſay, that this is the way by which God Almighty worketh, becauſe it is paſt my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, yet it ſerves very well to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that the Omnipotence of God impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no contradiction; and is better than by pretence of magnifying the fineneſs of the divine Subſtance, to reduce it to a Spright or Phantaſm, which is Nothing.</p>
                     <p>A <hi>Perſon,</hi> [Lat.] <hi>Perſona,</hi> ſignifies an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Subſtance, that acteth any thing in his own or anothers Name, or by his own or anothers Authority. Of this Definition there can be no other proof than from the uſe of that word, in ſuch Latin Authors as were eſteem'd the moſt skilful in their own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, of which number was <hi>Cicero.</hi> But <hi>Cicero,</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Atticus,</hi> ſaith thus, <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus ſustineo tres Perſonas, Mei, Adverſarii, &amp; Judicis:</hi> That is, I that am but one man, ſuſtain three Perſons; mine own Perſon, the Perſon of my Adverſary, and the Perſon of the Judge. <hi>Cicero</hi> was here the Subſtance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent, one man; and becauſe he pleaded for himſelf, he calls himſelf, his own Perſon; and again, becauſe he pleaded for his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, he ſays, he ſuſtained the Perſon of his Adverſary; and laſtly, becauſe he himſelf gave the Sentence, he ſays, he ſuſtained the Perſon of the Judge. In the ſame ſence we
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33138:23"/>uſe the word in Engliſh vulgarly, calling him that acteth by his own Authority, his own Perſon, and him that acteth by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of another, the Perſon of that other. And thus we have the exact meaning of the word <hi>Perſon.</hi> The Greek Tongue cannot render it; for <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>is properly a Face, and Metaphorically, a Vizard of an Actor upon the Stage. How then did the Greek Fathers render the word <hi>Perſon,</hi> as it is in the bleſſed Trinity? Not well. Inſtead of the word <hi>Perſon</hi> they put <hi>Hypostaſis,</hi> which ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies Subſtance, from whence it might be inferr'd, that the three Perſons in the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are three divine Subſtances, that is, three Gods. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, they could not uſe, becauſe Face and Vizard are neither of them honourable Attributes of God, nor explicative of the meaning of the Greek Church. Therefore the Latin (and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Engliſh) Church renders <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſis</hi> every where in <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his Creed by <hi>Perſon.</hi> But the word <hi>Hypostatical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> is rightly retained and uſed by Divines, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Union of two Hypoſtaſes, that is, of two Subſtances or Natures in the Perſon of Chriſt. But ſeeing they alſo hold the Soul of our Saviour to be a Subſtance, which though ſeparated from his Body, ſubſiſted neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in it ſelf, and conſequently before it was ſeparated from his Body upon the Croſs,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33138:23"/>was a diſtinct Nature from his Body, how will they avoid this Objection, That then Chriſt had three Natures, three Hypoſtaſes, without granting, that <hi>his Reſurrection was a new vivification, and not a return of his Soul out of Heaven into the Grave?</hi> The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is not determined by the Church. Thus far in explication of the words that occur in this Controverſie. Now I return again to his Lordſhip's Diſcourſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>When they have taken away all incorporeal Spirits, what do they leave God himſelf to be? He who is the Fountain of all Being, from whom and in whom all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures have their Being, muſt needs have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Being of his own. And what real Being can God have among Bodies and Accidents? for they have left nothing elſe in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. Then <hi>T. H.</hi> may move the ſame Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of God, which he did of Devils. <hi>I would gladly know in what Claſſis of Entities, the Biſhop ranketh God?</hi> Infinite Being and participated Being are not of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Yet to ſpeak according to humane ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, (apprehenſion and comprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on differ much: <hi>T. H.</hi> confeſſeth that natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reaſon doth dictate to us, that God is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, yet natural Reaſon cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Infiniteneſs of God) I place him among incorporeal Subſtances or Spirits, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath been pleaſed to place himſelf in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33138:24"/>that rank, <hi>God is a Spirit.</hi> Of which place <hi>T. H.</hi> giveth his opinion, that it is unintelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible, and all others of the ſame nature, <hi>and fall not under humane understanding.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>They who deny all incorporeal Subſtances, can underſtand nothing by God, but either Nature, (not <hi>Naturam naturantem,</hi> that is, a real Author of Nature, but <hi>Naturam natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratam,</hi> that is, the orderly concourſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Cauſes, as <hi>T. H.</hi> ſeemeth to intimate) or a fiction of the Brain, without real Being, cheriſhed for advantage and politick Ends, as a profitable Error, howſoever dignified with the glorious title of <hi>the eternal Cauſe of all things.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>To his Lordſhip's Queſtion here, What I leave God to be, I anſwer, I leave him to be a moſt pure, ſimple, inviſible Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Corporeal. By Corporeal I mean a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance that has Magnitude, and ſo mean all learned men, Divines and others, though perhaps there be ſome common people ſo rude as to call nothing Body, but what they can ſee and feel. To his ſecond Queſtion, What real Being he can have amongſt Bodies and Accidents, I anſwer, The Being of a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, not of a Spright. If I ſhould ask any the moſt ſubtil Diſtinguiſher, what middle na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture there were between an infinitely ſubtil Subſtance, and a meer Thought or Phantaſm, by what Name could he call it? He might
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33138:24"/>call it perhaps an Incorporeal Subſtance, and ſo <hi>Incorporeal</hi> ſhall paſs for a middle nature between <hi>Infinitely ſubtil</hi> and <hi>Nothing,</hi> and be leſs ſubtil than Infinitely ſubtil, and yet more ſubtil than a thought. 'Tis granted (he ſays) that the Nature of God is incomprehenſible. Doth it therefore follow, that we may give to the divine Subſtance what negative Name we pleaſe? Becauſe he ſays, the whole di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Subſtance is here and there and every where throughout the World, and that the Soul of a man is here and there and every where throughout man's Body, muſt we therefore take it for a Myſtery of Chriſtian Religion, upon his or any Schoolman's word, without the Scripture, which calls nothing a Myſtery but the Incarnation of the eternal God? Or is Incorporeal a Myſtery, when not at all mentioned in the Bible, but to the contrary 'tis written, <hi>That the fulneſs of the Deity was bodily in Christ?</hi> When the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing is incomprehenſible, I can acquieſce in the Scripture, but when the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of words are incomprehenſible, I cannot acquieſce in the Authority of a School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>We have ſeen what his Principles are concerning the Deity, they are full as bad or worſe concerning the Trinity. Hear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. <hi>A perſon is he that is repreſented as often as he is repreſented. And therefore God who
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33138:25"/>has been repreſented, that is, perſonated thrice, may properly enough be ſaid to be three Perſons, though neither the word Perſon nor Trinity be aſcribed to him in the Bible.</hi> And a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>To conclude, the doctrine of the Trinity as far as can be gathered directly from the Sori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, is in ſubstance this, that the God who is always one and the ſame, was the Perſon repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by Moſes, the Perſon repreſented by his Son incarnate, and the Perſon repreſented by the Apostles. As repreſented by the Apostles, the holy Spirit by which they ſpake is God. As repreſented by his Son that was God and Man, the Son is that God. As repreſented by Moſes, and the High Prieſts, the Father, that is to ſay, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Christ is that God. From whence we may gather the reaſon why thoſe Names, Father, Son, and Holy Ghost, in the ſignification of the Godhead, are never uſed in the Old Testament. For they are Perſons, that is, they have their Names from repreſenting, which could not be, till divers Perſons had repreſented God, in ruling or in directing under him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Who is ſo bold as blind <hi>Bayard?</hi> The Emblem of a little Boy attempting to lade all the Water out of the Sea with a Cockle-ſhell, doth ſit <hi>T. H.</hi> as exactly as if it had been ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for him, who thinketh to meaſure the profound and inſcrutable Myſteries of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, by his own ſilly, ſhallow conceits. What
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33138:25"/>is now become of the great adorable Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the bleſſed undivided Trinity? It is ſhrunk into nothing? Upon his grounds there was a time when there was no Trinity. And we muſt blot theſe words out of our Creed, <hi>The Father eternal, the Son eternal, and the Holy Ghost eternal.</hi> And theſe other words out of our Bibles, <hi>Let us make man after our Image.</hi> Unleſs we mean that this was a conſultation of God with <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Apoſtles. What is now become of the eternal generation of the Son of God, if this Sonſhip did not begin until about 4000 years after the Creation were expired? Upon theſe grounds every King hath as many <hi>Perſons,</hi> as there be Juſtices of Peace, and petty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables in his Kingdom. Upon this account God Almighty hath as many <hi>Perſons,</hi> as there have been Soveraign Princes in the World ſince <hi>Adam.</hi> According to this reckoning each one of us like ſo many <hi>Geryons,</hi> may have as many <hi>Perſons</hi> as we pleaſe to make Procurations. Such bold preſumption requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth another manner of confutation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>As for the words recited, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs there is a fault in the Ratiocination, which nevertheleſs his Lordſhip hath not diſcovered, but no Impiety. All that he objecteth is, That it followeth hereupon, that there be as many Perſons of a King, as there be petty Conſtables in his Kingdom. And ſo there
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:33138:26"/>are, or elſe he cannot be obeyed. But I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaid that a King, and every one of his Perſons are the ſame Subſtance. The fault I here made, and ſaw not was this; I was to prove, That it is no contradiction (as <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and Heathen Scoffers would have it) to ſay of God, he was One and Three. I ſaw the true definition of the word <hi>Perſon</hi> would ſerve my turn in this manner; God in his own Perſon both created the World, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted a Church in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> uſing therein the Miniſtry of <hi>Moſes;</hi> the ſame God in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Son God and Man redeemed the ſame World, and the ſame Church; the ſame God in the Perſon of the Holy Ghoſt ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the ſame Church, and all the faithful men in the World. Is not this a clear proof, that it is no contradiction to ſay that God is three Perſons and one Subſtance? And doth not the Church diſtinguiſh the Perſons in the ſame manner? See the words of our Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm. Queſt. <hi>What dost thou chiefly learn in theſe Articles of the Belief? Anſw.</hi> Firſt, I learn to believe in God the Father, that hath made me and all the World; Secondly, In God the Son, who hath redeemed me and all Mankind; Thirdly, In God the Holy Ghoſt, that hath ſanctified me and all the elect people of God. But at what time was the Church ſanctified? Was it not on the day of <hi>Pentecost,</hi> in the deſcending of the Holy
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33138:26"/>Ghoſt upon the apoſtles? His Lordſhip all this while hath catched nothing. 'Tis I that catched my ſelf, for ſaying, (inſtead of, <hi>By the Ministry of Moſes</hi>) in the Perſon of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> But this Error I no ſooner ſaw, then I no leſs publickly corrected then I had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it, in my <hi>Leviathan</hi> converted into Latin, which by this time I think is printed beyond the Seas with this alteration, and alſo with the omiſſion of ſome ſuch paſſages as Strangers are not concerned in. And I had corrected this Error ſooner, if I had ſooner found it. For though I was told by Dr. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Dureſme,</hi> that the place above-cited was not applicable enough to the Doctrine of the Trinity, yet I could not in reviewing the ſame eſpy the defect till of late, when being ſollicited from beyond Sea to tranſlate the Book into Latin, and fearing ſome other man might do it not to my liking, I examined this paſſage and others of the like ſence more narrowly. But how concludes his Lordſhip out of this, that I put out of the Creed theſe words, <hi>The Father eternal, the Son eternal, the Holy Ghost eternal?</hi> Or theſe words, <hi>Let us make man after our Image,</hi> out of the Bible. Which laſt words neither I nor <hi>Bellarmine</hi> put out of the Bible, but we both put them out of the number of good Arguments to prove the Trinity; for it is no unuſual thing in the Hebrew, as may be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33138:27"/>ſeen by <hi>Bellarmine</hi>'s quotations, to joyn a Noun of the plural Number with a Verb of the ſingular. And we may ſay alſo of many other Texts of Scripture alledged to prove the Trinity, that they are not ſo firm as that high Article requireth. But mark his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Scholaſtick charity in the laſt words of this period, <hi>Such bold preſumption requireth another manner of confutation.</hi> This Biſhop, and others of his opinion had been in their Element, if they had been Biſhops in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> time.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Concerning God the Son, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what he had ſaid elſewhere, where he calleth him <hi>God and Man,</hi> and <hi>the Son of God incarnate,</hi> he doubteth not to ſay, that <hi>the word</hi> Hypoſtatical <hi>is canting.</hi> As if the ſame Perſon could be both God and Man without a Perſonal, that is, an Hypoſtatical Union of the two Natures of God and Man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>If Chriſtian Profeſſion be (as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is in <hi>England</hi>) a Law, and if it be of the nature of a Law to be made known to all men that are to obey it, in ſuch manner as they may have no excuſe for diſobedience from their ignorance, then without doubt all words unknown to the people, and as to them inſignificant, are Canting. The word <hi>Substance</hi> is underſtood by the Vulgar well enough, when it is ſaid of a Body, but in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33138:27"/>other ſence not at all, except for their Riches. But the word <hi>Hypostatical</hi> is underſtood only by thoſe, and but few of thoſe that are lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Greek Tongue, and is properly uſed, as I have ſaid before, of the Union of the two Natures of Chriſt in one Perſon. So likewiſe <hi>Conſubstantial</hi> in the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, is properly ſaid of the Trinity. But to an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man that underſtands neither Greek nor Latin, and yet is as much concerned as his Lordſhip was, the word <hi>Hypostatical</hi> is no leſs Canting than <hi>Eternal now.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>He alloweth every man who is commanded by his lawful Soveraign, <hi>to deny Chriſt with his tongue before men.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>I allow it in ſome Caſes, and to ſome men, which his Lordſhip knew well enough, but would not mention. I alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for it, in the place cited, both Reaſon and Scripture, though his Lordſhip thought it not expedient to take notice of either. If it be true that I have ſaid, why does he blame it? If falſe, why offers he no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt it, neither from Scripture nor from Reaſon? Or why does he not ſhow that the Text I cite is non applicable to the Queſtion, or not well interpreted by me. Firſt, He barely cites it, becauſe he thought the words would ſound harſhly, and make a Reader admire them for Impiety. But I hope I ſhall ſo well inſtruct my Reader are I leave
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33138:28"/>this place, that this his petty Art will have no effect. Secondly, The Cauſe why he omitted my Arguments was, That he could not anſwer them. Laſtly, The Cauſe why he urgeth neither Scripture nor Reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it was, That he ſaw none ſufficient. My Argument from Scripture was this, (<hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan,</hi> pag. 271.) taken out of 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 5.17. where <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> ſaith to <hi>Eliſha</hi> the Prophet, <hi>Thy ſervant will henceforth offer neither burnt-offering nor ſacrifice to other Gods, but unto the Lord. In this thing the Lord pardon thy ſervant, that when my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter goeth into the houſe of Rimmon to worſhip there, and he leaneth on my hand, and I bow my ſelf in the houſe of Rimmon: when I bow my ſelf in the houſe of Rimmon, the Lord par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thy ſervant in this thing, and he ſaid unto him, Go in peace.</hi> What can be ſaid to this? Did not <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſay it from God? Or is not this Anſwer of the Prophet a permiſſion? When St. <hi>Paul</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> commanded the <hi>Christians</hi> of their time to obey their Princes, which then were Heathens and Enemies of Chriſt, did they mean they ſhould loſe their Lives for diſobedience? Did they not rather mean they ſhould preſerve both their Lives and their Faith, (believing in Chriſt as they did) by this denial of the tongue, having no command to the contrary? If in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom a <hi>Mahometan</hi> ſhould be made by terror
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33138:28"/>to deny <hi>Mahomet</hi> and go to Church with us, would any man condemn this <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan?</hi> A denyal with the mouth may perhaps be prejudicial to the power of the Church, but to retain the Faith of Chriſt ſtedfaſtly in his Heart, cannot be prejudicial to his Soul that hath undertaken no charge to preach to Wolves, whom they know will deſtroy them. About the time of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice,</hi> there was a Canon made (which is extant in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil) concerning thoſe that being Chriſtians had been ſeduced, not terrified, to a deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al of Chriſt, and again repenting, deſired to be readmitted into the Church; in which Canon it was ordain'd that thoſe men ſhould be no otherwiſe readmitted than to be in the number of the Catechiſed, and not to be admitted to the Communion till a great many years penitence. Surely the Church then would have been more merciful to them that did the ſame upon terror of preſent death and torments.</p>
                     <p>Let us now ſee what his Lordſhip might, though but colourably, have alledged from Scripture againſt it. There be three places only that ſeem to favour his Lordſhip's opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. The firſt is where <hi>Peter</hi> denyed Chriſt, and weepeth. The ſecond is, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.29. <hi>Then</hi> Peter <hi>and the other Apoſtles an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and ſaid, we ought to obey God rather
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33138:29"/>than men.</hi> The third is, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.9. <hi>But he that denyeth me, ſhall be denyed before the Angels of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>For anſwer to theſe Texts, I muſt repeat what I have written, and his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip read in my <hi>Leviathan,</hi> pag. 362. <hi>For an unlearned man that is in the power of an Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous King, or State, if commanded on pain of Death to worſhip before an Idol, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, he detesteth the Idol in his Heart, he doth well; though if he had the fortitude to ſuffer Death, rather than worſhip it, he ſhould do better. But if a Pastor, who as Christ's Meſſenger has undertaken to teach Christ's Doctrine to all Nations ſhould do the ſame, it were not only a ſinful Scandal in reſpect of other Christian Mens Conſciences, but a perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious forſaking of his Charge.</hi> In which words I diſtinguiſh between a Paſtor and one of the Sheep of his Flock. St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſinned in denying Chriſt; and ſo does every Paſtor that having undertaken the Charge of Preaching the Goſpel in the Kingdom of an Infidel, where he could expect at the undertaking of his Charge no leſs than Death. And why, but becauſe he violates his Truſt in doing contrary to his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. St. <hi>Peter</hi> was an Apoſtle of Chriſt, and bound by his voluntary undertaking of that Office, not only to Confeſs Chriſt, but alſo to Preach him before thoſe Infidels whom he
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33138:29"/>knew would (like Wolves) devour him. And therefore when <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles were forbidden to preach Chriſt they gave this Anſwer, <hi>We ought to obey God rather than Men.</hi> And it was to his Diſciples only which had undertaken that Office, that Chriſt ſaith, <hi>he that denyeth me before Men, ſhall be denyed before the Angels of God.</hi> And ſo I think I have ſufficiently anſwered this place, and ſhewed that I do not allow the denying of Chriſt, upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny colour of Torments, to his Lordſhip, nor to any other that has undertaken the Office of a Preacher. Which if he think right, he will perhaps in this caſe put himſelf into the number of thoſe whom he calls merciful Doctors, whereas now he extends his ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity beyond the bounds of common equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. He has read <hi>Cicero,</hi> and perhaps this Story in him. The Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> would have ſent <hi>Cicero</hi> to treat of Peace with <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Antonius,</hi> but when <hi>Cicero</hi> had ſhewed them the juſt fear he had of being killed by him, he was excuſed; and if they had forced him to it, and he by terror turned Enemy to them, he had in equity been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable. But his Lordſhip I believe did write this more valiantly than he would have acted it.</p>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:33138:30"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>He Depoſeth Chriſt from his true Kingly Office, making his <hi>Kingdom not to Commence or begin before the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And <hi>the Regiment wherewith Christ Governeth his Faithful in this Life, is not properly a Kingdom, but a Pastoral Office, or a right to Teach.</hi> And a little after, <hi>Christ had not Kingly Authority committed to him by his Father in this World, but only Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliary and Doctrinal.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>How do I take away Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office? He neither draws it by Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence from my Words, nor offers any Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument at all againſt my Doctrine. The words he cites are in the Contents of <hi>Chap.</hi> 17. <hi>de Cive.</hi> In the Body of the Chapter it is thus. The time of Chriſt's being upon the Earth is called in Scripture the <hi>Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> often, but the <hi>Kingdom</hi> never. <hi>When the Son of God comes in Majeſty, and all the Angels with him, then he ſhall ſit on the ſeat of Majeſty. My Kingdom is not of this World. God ſent not his Son that he ſhould judge the World. I came not to judge the World, but to ſave the World. Man, who made me a Judge or Divider amongſt you? Let thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom come.</hi> And other words to the ſame purpoſe; out of which it is clear that Chriſt took upon him no Regal Power upon Earth before his Aſſumption. But at his Aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption his Apoſtles asked him if he would
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33138:30"/>then reſtore the Kingdom to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and he anſwered, it was not for them to know. So that hitherto Chriſt had not taken that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice upon him, unleſs his Lordſhip think that the Kingdom of God, and the Kingdom of Chriſt be two diſtinct Kingdoms. From the Aſſumption ever ſince, all true Chriſtians ſay daily in their Prayers, <hi>Thy Kingdom come.</hi> But his Lordſhip had perhaps forgot that. But when then beginneth Chriſt to be a King? I ſay it ſhall be then when he comes again in Majeſty with all the Angels. And even then he ſhall reign (as he is Man) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Father. For St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.25, 26. <hi>He must reign till he hath put all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies under his feet; the last Enemy that ſhall be destroyed is Death.</hi> But when ſhall God the Father reign again? St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in the ſame <hi>Chapter verſe</hi> 28. <hi>When all things ſhall be ſubdued unto him, then ſhall the Son alſo himſelf be ſubject unto him that put all things under him, that God may be all in all.</hi> And <hi>verſe</hi> 24. <hi>Then cometh the end, when he ſhall have delivered up the Kingdom to God even the Father; when he ſhall have put down all Rule, Authority and Power.</hi> This is at the Reſurrection. And by this it is manifeſt, that his Lordſhip was not ſo well verſed in Scripture, as he ought to have been.</p>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:33138:31"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>He taketh away his Prieſtly or Propitiatory Office; <hi>And although this Act of our Redemption be not alwayes in Scripture called a Sacrifice and Oblation, but ſometimes a Price, yet by Price we are not to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand any thing, by the value whereof he could claim right to a Pardon for us from his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended Father, but that Price which God the Father was pleaſed in mercy to demand.</hi> And again, <hi>Not that the Death of one Man though without ſin, can ſatisfie for the Offences of all Men in the rigour of Juſtice, but in the mercy of God, that ordained ſuch Sacrifices for ſin, as he was pleaſed in mercy to accept.</hi> He knoweth no difference between one who is meer man, and one who was both God and man; between a <hi>Levitical</hi> Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and the All-ſufficient Sacrifice of the Croſs; between the Blood of a Calf, and the precious Blood of the Son of God.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, I know there is a difference between Blood and Blood, but not any ſuch as can make a difference in the Caſe here queſtioned. Our Saviour's Blood was moſt precious, but ſtill it was Humane Blood; and I hope his Lordſhip did never think otherwiſe, or that it was not accepted by his Father for our Redemption.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>And touching the Prophetical Office of Chriſt, I do much doubt whether he do believe in earneſt, that there is any
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33138:31"/>ſuch thing as Prophecy in the World. He maketh very little difference between a <hi>Prophet</hi> and a <hi>Mad-man,</hi> and <hi>a Demoniack. And if there were nothing elſe</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that bewrayed their madneſs, yet that very arroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch inſpiration to themſelves, is Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enough.</hi> He maketh the pretence of Inſpiration in any man to be, and always to have been, <hi>on opinion pernicious to Peace, and tending to the diſſolution of all Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi> He ſubjecteth all Prophetical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations from God, to the ſole Pleaſure and Cenſure of the Soveraign Prince, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Authorize them, or to Exauctorate them. So as two Prophets prophecying the ſame thing at the ſame time, in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of two different Princes, the one ſhall be a true Prophet, the other a falſe. And Chriſt who had the approbation of no Soveraign Prince, upon his grounds, was to be reputed a falſe Prophet every where. <hi>Every man therefore ought to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der who is the Soveraign Prophet, that is to ſay, who it is that is Gods Vicegerent upon Earth, and hath next under God the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of governing Christian Men, and to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve for a Rule that Doctrine which in the Name of God he hath Commanded to be taught, and thereby to examine and try out the truth of thoſe Doctrines which pretended Prophets, with miracle, or without, ſhall at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33138:32"/>time advance,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And if he diſavow them, then no more to obey their Voice; or if he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them, then to obey them as Men, to whom God hath given a part of the Spirit of their Soveraign.</hi> Upon his Principles the caſe holdeth as well among <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> as <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Then he that teacheth Tranſubſtantiation in <hi>France,</hi> is a true Prophet; he that teacheth in it <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> a falſe Prophet. He that blaſphemeth Chriſt in <hi>Constantinople,</hi> a true Prophet; he that doth the ſame in <hi>Italy,</hi> a falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. Then <hi>Samuel</hi> was a falſe Prophet to conteſt with <hi>Saul</hi> a Soveraign Prophet: So was the Man of God who ſubmitted not to the more Divine and Prophetick Spirit of <hi>Jeroboam.</hi> And <hi>Elijah</hi> for reproving <hi>Ahab.</hi> Then <hi>Michaiah</hi> had but his deſerts, to be clapt up in Priſon, and fed with Bread of Affliction, and Water of Affliction, for da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to contradict <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Vice-gerent upon Earth.</hi> And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was juſtly thrown into a Dungeon, for Prophecying againſt <hi>Zedekiah</hi> his Liege Lord. If his Principles were true, it were ſtrange indeed, that none of all theſe Princes, nor any other that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was in the World, ſhould underſtand their own Priviledges. And yet more ſtrange, that God Almighty ſhould take the part of ſuch Rebellious Prophets, and juſtifie their Propheſies by the Event, if is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33138:32"/>were true that <hi>none but the Soveraign in a Christian</hi> (the reaſon is the ſame for <hi>Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh) Commonwealth can take notice, what is or what is not the Word of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>To remove his Lordſhip's doubt in the firſt place, I confeſs there was true Propheſie and true Prophets in the Church of God, from <hi>Abraham</hi> down to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our the greateſt Prophet of all, and the laſt of the Old Teſtament, and firſt of the New. After our Saviour's time, till the death of St. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle, there were true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in the Church of Chriſt, Prophets to whom God ſpake ſupernaturally, and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified the truth of their Miſſion by Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Of thoſe that in the Scripture are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Prophets without Miracles, and for this cauſe only, that they ſpake in the Name of God to Men, and in the name of Men to God, there are, have been, and ſhall be in the Church innumerable. Such a Prophet was his Lordſhip, and ſuch are all Paſtors in the Chriſtian Church. But the Queſtion here is of thoſe Prophets that from the Mouth of God foretell things future, or do other Miracle. Of this kind I deny there has been any ſince the Death of St. <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt. If any Man find fault with this, he ought to name ſome Man or other whom we are bound to acknowledge that they have done a Miracle, caſt out a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33138:33"/>or cured any Diſeaſe by the ſole Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Divine Majeſty. We are not bound to truſt to the Legend of the <hi>Roman</hi> Saints, nor to the Hiſtory written by <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitius</hi> of the Life of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> or to any other Fables of the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy, nor to ſuch things as were pretended to be done by ſome Divines here in the time of King <hi>James.</hi> Secondly, he ſays I make little dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between a <hi>Prophet</hi> and a <hi>Mad-man,</hi> or <hi>Demoniack;</hi> To which I ſay he accuſes me falſly. I ſay only thus much, <hi>That I ſee nothing at all in the Scripture that requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a belief, that Demoniacks were any other-thing than Madmen.</hi> And this is alſo made very probable out of Scripture by a worthy Divine Mr. <hi>Meade.</hi> But concerning Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, I ſay only that the <hi>Jews</hi> both under the Old Teſtament and under the New, took them to be all one with <hi>Mad-men</hi> and <hi>Demoniacks.</hi> And prove it out of Scripture by many places both of the Old and New Teſtament. Thirdly, that the pretence or arrogating to ones ſelf Divine Inſpiration, is argument enough to ſhew a Man is <hi>Mad,</hi> is my opinion; but his Lordſhip underſtands not <hi>Inſpiration</hi> in the ſame ſence that I do. He underſtands it properly of God's breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into a Man, or pouring into him the Divine Subſtance, or Divine Graces, and in that ſence, he that arrogateth Inſpiration
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:33138:33"/>into himſelf, neither underſtands what he ſaith, nor makes others to underſtand him, which is properly Madneſs in ſome degree. But I underſtand <hi>Inſpiration</hi> in the Scripture Metaphorically, for Gods guidance of our minds to Truth and Piety. Fourthly, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he ſays, I make the pretence of <hi>Inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to be pernicious to Peace. I anſwer, that I think his Lordſhip was of my Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for he called thoſe Men which in the late Civil War pretended the Spirit, and New Light, and to be the only faithful men <hi>Phanaticks;</hi> for he called them in his Book, and did call them in his Life time <hi>Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi> And what is a <hi>Phanatick</hi> but a <hi>Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and what can be more pernicious to Peace than the Revelations that were by theſe <hi>Phanaticks</hi> pretended? I do not ſay there were Doctrines of other Men, not called <hi>Phanaticks</hi> as pernicious to Peace, as theirs were, and in great part a cauſe of thoſe troubles. Fifthly, from that I make Prophetical Revelations ſubject to the examination of the Lawful Soveraign, he inferreth, that two Prophets prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame thing at the ſame time, in the Dominions of two different Princes, the one ſhall be a true Prophet, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a falſe. This conſequence is not good, for ſeeing they teach different Doctrines, they cannot both of them confirm their
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:33138:34"/>Doctrine with Miracles. But this I prove (in the <hi>page</hi> 232 he citeth) that, whether either of their Doctrines ſhall be taught publickly or not, 'tis in the power of the Soveraign of the Place only to determine. Nay, I ſay now further, if a Prophet come to any private Man in the Name of God, that Man ſhall be Judge whether he be a true Prophet or not, before he obey him. See 1 <hi>John</hi> 4. 1. Sixthly, whereas he ſays, that upon my grounds Chriſt was to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted a falſe Prophet every where, becauſe his Doctrine was received no where. His Lordſhip had read my Book more negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently than was fit for one that would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute it. My ground is this, that Chriſt in right of his Father was King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and conſequently Supream Prophet, and Judge of all Prophets. What other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thought of his Propheſies, is nothing to the purpoſe. I never ſaid that Princes can make Doctrines or Propheſies true or falſe, but I ſay every Soveraign Prince has a right to prohibite the publick Teaching of them, whether falſe or true. But what an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight is it in a Divine to ſay, that Chriſt had the Approbation of no Soveraign Prince, when he had the Approbation of God, who was King of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and Chriſt his Vice-Roy, and the whole Scripture written (<hi>Joh.</hi> 20.31.) to prove it? When his Miracles de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33138:34"/>it; when <hi>Pilate</hi> confeſſed it; and when the Apoſtles Office was to proclaim it? Seventhly, If we muſt not conſider in points of Chriſtian Faith who is the Soveraign Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, that is, who is next under Chriſt our Supream Head and Governor, I wiſh his Lordſhip would have cleared, ere he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, theſe few Queſtions. Is there not need of ſome Judge of Controverted Doctrines? I think no man can deny it, that has ſeen the Rebellion that followed the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie here between <hi>Gomar</hi> and <hi>Arminius.</hi> There muſt therefore be a Judge of Doctrines. But (ſays the Biſhop) not the King. Who then? Shall Dr. <hi>Bramhall</hi> be this Judge? As profitable an Office as it is, he was more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt than to ſay that. Shall a private Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man have it? No man ever thought that. Shall it be given to a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Miniſter? No; 'tis unreaſonable. Shall a Synod of <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> have it? No; For moſt of the <hi>Presbyters</hi> in the Primitive Church were undoubtedly ſubordinate to Biſhops, and the reſt were Biſhops. Who then? A Synod of Biſhops? Very well. His Lordſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too modeſt to undertake the whole Power would have been contented with the ſix and twentieth part. But ſuppoſe it in a Synod of Biſhops, who ſhall call them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? The King. What if he will not? Who ſhould Excommunicate him, or if he
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33138:35"/>deſpiſe your Excommunication, who ſhall ſend forth a Writ of <hi>Significavit?</hi> No; all this was far from his Lordſhips thoughts. The power of the Clergy, unleſs it be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held legally by the King, or illegally by the Multitude amounts to nothing. But for the Multitude, <hi>Suarez</hi> and the School-men will never gain them, becauſe they are not underſtood. Beſides there be very few Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops that can act a Sermon (which is a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſant part of <hi>Rhetorick</hi>) So well as divers <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Phanatick</hi> Preachers can do. I conclude therefore, that his Lordſhip could not poſſibly believe that the Supream Judicature in matter of Religion could any where be ſo well placed as in the Head of the Church, which is the King. And ſo his Lordſhip and I think the ſame thing; but becauſe his Lordſhip knew not how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it, he was angry with me becauſe I did it. He ſays further that <hi>by my Principles, he that blaſphemeth Christ at</hi> Conſtantinople <hi>is a true Prophet,</hi> as if a man that blaſphemeth Chriſt, to approve his Blaſphemy can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a Miracle; for by my principles no Man is a Prophet whoſe Propheſie is not confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God with a Miracle. In the laſt place out of this, That the lawful Soveraign is the Judge of Propheſie, he deduces That then <hi>Samuel</hi> and other Prophets were falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets that conteſted with their Soveraigns.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33138:35"/>As for <hi>Samuel</hi> he was at that time the Judge, that is to ſay the Soveraign Prince in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſo acknowledged by <hi>Saul.</hi> For <hi>Saul</hi> received the Kingdom (from God himſelf, who had right to give and take it) by the hands of <hi>Samuel.</hi> And God gave it him to himſelf only, and not to his Seed; though if he had obeyed God, he would have ſetled it alſo upon his Seed. The Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God was, that he ſhould not ſpare <hi>Agag. Saul</hi> obeyed not. God therefore ſent <hi>Samuel</hi> to tell him that he was rejected. For all this <hi>Samuel</hi> went not about to reſiſt <hi>Saul.</hi> That he cauſed <hi>Agag</hi> to be ſlain, was with <hi>Sauls</hi> conſent. Laſtly, <hi>Saul</hi> confeſſes his ſin. Where is this conteſting with <hi>Saul?</hi> After this God ſent <hi>Samuel</hi> to anoint <hi>David,</hi> not that he ſhould depoſe <hi>Saul,</hi> but ſucceed him, the Sons of <hi>Saul</hi> having never had a right of Succeſſion. Nor did ever <hi>David</hi> make War on <hi>Saul,</hi> or ſo much as reſiſt him, but fled from his perſecution. But when <hi>Saul</hi> was dead, then indeed he claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his right againſt the Houſe of <hi>Saul.</hi> What Rebellion or Reſiſtance could his Lordſhip find here, either in <hi>Samùel</hi> or in <hi>David?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, all theſe Tranſactions are ſupernatural, and oblige not to imitation. Is there any Prophet or Prieſt now that can ſet up in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> another King by pretence of Propheſie or Religion? What
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33138:36"/>did <hi>Jeroboam</hi> to the man of God 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13) that propheſied againſt the Altar in <hi>Bethel,</hi> without firſt doing a Miracle, but offer to ſeize him for ſpeaking (as he thought) raſhly of the Kings Act; and after the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous withering of his Hand, deſire the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet to pray for him? The ſin of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> was not his diſtruſt of the Prophet, but his Idolatry. He was the ſole Judge of the truth which the man of God uttered againſt the Altar, and the proceſs agreeable to equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. What is the ſtory of <hi>Eliah</hi> and <hi>Ahab</hi> (1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.) but a confirmation of the Right, even of <hi>Ahab</hi> to be the Judge of Propheſie? <hi>Eliah</hi> told <hi>Ahab,</hi> he had tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the Commandement of God. So may any Miniſter now tell his Soveraign, ſo he do it with ſincerity and diſcretion. <hi>Ahab</hi> told <hi>Eliah</hi> he troubled <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Upon this controverſie <hi>Eliah</hi> deſired tryal. Send, ſaith he, and aſſemble all <hi>Iſrael;</hi> Aſſemble alſo the Prophets of <hi>Baal</hi> four hundred and fifty. <hi>Ahab</hi> did ſo. The Queſtion is ſtated before the People thus, If the Lord be God, follow him; but if <hi>Baal</hi> follow him. Then upon the Altars of God and <hi>Baal</hi> were laid the Wood and the Bullocks; and the cauſe was to be judged by Fire from Heaven, to burn the Sacrifices; which <hi>Eliah</hi> procured, the Prophets of <hi>Baal</hi> could not procure, Was not this cauſe here Pleaded before <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab?</hi>
                        <pb n="65" facs="tcp:33138:36"/>The Sentence of <hi>Ahab</hi> is not requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; for <hi>Eliah</hi> from that time forward was no more perſecuted by <hi>Ahab,</hi> but only by his Wife <hi>Jezabel.</hi> The ſtory of <hi>Micaiah</hi> (2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 18.) is this, <hi>Ahab</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted the Prophets, four hundred in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, whether he ſhould proſper or not, in caſe he went with <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> King of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> to fight againſt the <hi>Syrians</hi> at <hi>Ramoth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilead.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Micaiah</hi> was alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and both the Kings <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> ſat together to hear what they ſhould prophecy. There was no Miracle done. The 400 pronounced Victory, <hi>Micaiah</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone the contrary. The King was Judge, and moſt concern'd in the event; nor had he received any Revelation in the buſineſs. What could he do more diſcreetly than to follow the Counſel of 400 rather than of one Man? But the event was contrary; for he was ſlain; but not for following the Counſel of the 400, but for his Murder of <hi>Naboth</hi> and his Idolatry. It was alſo a ſin in him, that he afflicted <hi>Micaiah</hi> in Priſon; but an unjuſt Judgment does not take away from any King his right of Judicature. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, what's all this, or that of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> which he cites laſt, to the Queſtion of who is Judge of Chriſtian Doctrine?</p>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:33138:37"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Neither doth he uſe God the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, more favourably than God the Son. Where St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, Holy men of God ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Spirit; He ſaith, <hi>By the Spirit, is meant the Voice of God in a Dream or Viſion Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural,</hi> which Dreams or Viſions, he maketh to be no more than <hi>imaginations which they had in their ſleep, or in an extaſie, which in every true Prophet were Supernatural, but in falſe Prophets were either natural or feigned,</hi> and more likely to be falſe than true. To ſay <hi>God hath ſpoken to him in a Dream, is no more than to ſay, he dreamed that God ſpake to him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>To ſay he hath ſeen a Viſion or heard a Voice, is to ſay, That he hath dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed between ſleeping and waking.</hi> So St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Holy Ghoſt is come to be their own imaginations, which might be either feigned, or miſtaken, or true. As if the Holy Ghoſt did enter only at their eyes, and at their ears, not into their underſtandings, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their minds; Or as if the Holy Ghoſt did not ſeal unto their hearts the truth and aſſurance of their Propheſies. Whether a new light be infuſed into their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, or new graces be inſpired into their heart, they are wrought, or cauſed, or crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted immediately by the Holy Ghoſt, And ſo are his <hi>imaginations,</hi> if they be Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural.</p>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:33138:37"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>For the places of my <hi>Leviathan</hi> he cites, they are all as they ſtand both true and clearly proved; the ſetting of them down by Fragments is no Refutation; nor offers he any Argument againſt them. His conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences are not deduced. I never ſaid that the Holy Ghoſt was an Imagination, or a Dream, or a Viſion, but that the Holy Ghoſt ſpake moſt often in the Scripture by Dreams and Viſions ſupernatural. The next words of his, <hi>As if the Holy Ghost did enter only at their eyes, and at their ears, not into their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandings, nor into their minds,</hi> I let paſs, becauſe I cannot underſtand them. His laſt words, <hi>Whether new light, &amp;c.</hi> I underſtand and approve.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>But he muſt needs fall into theſe abſurdities, who maketh but a jeſt of inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. <hi>They who pretend Divine inſpiration to be a ſupernatural entring of the Holy Ghoſt into a Man, are (as he thinks) in a very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Dilemma; for if they worſhip not the Men whom they conceive to be inſpired, they fall into impiety; and if they worſhip them, they commit Idolatry.</hi> So miſtaking the Holy Ghoſt to be corporeal, ſome thing that is blown into a Man, and the Graces of the Holy Ghoſt to be corporeal Graces. And <hi>the words, inpoured or infuſed virtue, and, inblown or inſpired virtue, are as abſurd and inſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, as a round Quadrangle.</hi> He reckons it
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33138:38"/>as a common error, That <hi>faith and ſanctity are not attained by study and reaſon, but by ſupernatural inſpiration or infuſion.</hi> And lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this for a firm ground; <hi>Faith and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity are indeed not very frequent, but yet they are not Miracles, but brought to paſs by Education, Diſcipline, Correction, and other natural wayes.</hi> I would ſee the greateſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagian of them all fly higher.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>I make here no jeſt of Inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Seriouſly, I ſay, that in the proper ſignification of the words <hi>Inſpiration</hi> and <hi>Infuſion,</hi> to ſay virtue is inſpired, or infuſed, is as abſurd as to ſay a Quadrangle is round. But Metaphorically, for Gods beſtowing of Faith, Grace, or other Vertue, thoſe words are intelligible enough.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſhould he trouble himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Holy Spirit, who acknowledgeth no Spirit but either a ſubtil fluid body, or a Ghoſt, or other Idol or Phantaſm of the imagination; who knoweth no inward Grace or intrinſecal Holyneſs? <hi>Holy is a word which in Gods Kingdom anſwereth to that which men in their Kingdoms uſe to call pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, or the Kings.</hi> And again, <hi>whereſoever the word Holy is taken properly, there is ſtill ſome thing ſignified of propriety gotten by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi> His Holineſs is a Relation, not a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; for inward ſanctification, or real infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed holineſs, in reſpect whereof the third,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33138:38"/>Perſon is called the Holy Ghoſt, becauſe he is not only holy in himſelf, but alſo maketh us holy, he is ſo great a ſtranger to it, that he doth altogether deny it, and diſclaim it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>The word <hi>Holy</hi> I had defined in the words which his Lordſhip here ſets down, and by the uſe thereof in the Scripture made it manifeſt, That that was the true ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word. There is nothing in Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more difficult than to determine the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of words. That difficulty excuſes him. He ſays that <hi>Holineſs</hi> (in my ſence) is a Relation, not a Quality. All the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed agree that Quality is an Accident, ſo that in attributing to God <hi>Holineſs</hi> (as a Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) he contradicts himſelf; for he has in the beginning of this his diſcourſe denyed (and rightly) that any Accident is in God, ſaying whatſoever is in God is the Divine Subſtance. He affirms alſo, that to attribute any Accident to God, is to deny the ſimplicity of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Subſtance. And thus his Lordſhip makes God, as I do, a Corporeal Spirit. Both here, and throughout, he diſcovers ſo much ignorance, as had he charged me with error only, and not with Atheiſm, I ſhould not have thought it neceſſary to anſwer him.</p>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:33138:39"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>We are taught in our Creed to believe the Catholick or Univerſal Church. But <hi>T. H.</hi> teacheth us the contrary, <hi>That if there be more Chriſtian Churches than one, all of them together are not one Church perſonally,</hi> And more plainly, <hi>Now if the whole number of Chriſtians be not contained in one Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, they are not one Perſon, nor is there an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, that hath any Authority over them.</hi> And again, <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church is not one Perſon, of which it can be ſaid, that it hath done, or Decreed, or Ordained, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, or Abſolved.</hi> This doth quite overthrow all the Authority of General Councils.</p>
                     <p>All other Men diſtinguiſh between the Church and the Common-wealth; only <hi>T. H.</hi> maketh them to be one and the ſame thing. <hi>The Common-wealth of Christian men, and the Church of the ſame, are altogether the ſame thing, called by two names, for two rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. For the matter of the Church and of the Common-wealth is the ſame, namely the ſame Christian men; and the Form is the ſame, which conſiſteth in the lawful power of convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them.</hi> And hence he concludeth, That <hi>every Chriſtian Common-wealth is a Church endowed with all ſpiritual Authority.</hi> And yet more fully, <hi>The Church if it be one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is the ſame thing with the Common-wealth of Christians, called a Common-wealth, becauſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33138:39"/>it conſisteth of men united in one Perſon their Soveraign; And a Church becauſe it conſisteth in Christian men united in one Christian So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign.</hi> Upon which account there was no Chriſtian Church in theſe Parts of the World, for ſome hundreds of years after Chriſt, becauſe there was no Chriſtian So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. A.</speaker>
                     <p>For anſwer to this Period, I ſay only this, That taking the Church (as I do in all thoſe places) for a company of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an men on Earth incorporated into one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that can ſpeak, command, or do any act of a Perſon, all that he citeth out of what I have written is true; and that all private Conventicles, though their belief be right, are not properly called Churches; and that there is not any one Univerſal Church here on Earth which is a Perſon indued with Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority univerſal to govern all Chriſtian men on Earth, no more than there is one Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Soveraign Prince or State on Earth that hath right to govern all Mankind. I deny alſo that the whole Clergy of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Kingdom or State being aſſembled, are the repreſentative of that Church further than the Civil Laws permits; or can lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſemble themſelves, unleſs by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or by the leave of the Soveraign Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Power. I ſay further, that the denyal of this point tendeth in <hi>England</hi> towards
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33138:40"/>the taking away of the Kings Supremacy in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical. But his Lordſhip has not here denyed any thing of mine, becauſe he has done no more but ſet down my words. He ſays further, that this Doctrine deſtroyes the Authority of all General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils; which I confeſs. Nor hath any Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council at this day in this Kingdom the force of a Law, nor ever had, but by the Authority of the King.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Neither is he more Orthodox con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Holy Scriptures, <hi>Hitherto,</hi> that is, <hi>for the</hi> Books of <hi>Moſes, the power of mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture Canonical, was in the Civil Soveraign.</hi> The like he ſaith of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, made Canonical by <hi>Eſdras.</hi> And of the New Teſtament, That <hi>it was not the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles which made their own Writings Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, but every Convert made them ſo to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> Yet with this reſtriction, That <hi>until the Soveraign Ruler had preſcribed them, they were but Counſel and Advice, which whether good or bad, he that was counſelled might without injustice refuſe to obſerve, and being contrary to the Laws establiſhed, could not without injuſtice obſerve.</hi> He maketh the Primitive Chriſtians to have been in a pretty condition. Certainly the Goſpel was contrary to the Laws then eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But moſt plainly, <hi>The word of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter of the Scripture is the word of God.</hi>
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:33138:40"/>And the <hi>ſame is the Interpreter of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and the Soveraign Judge of all Doctrines,</hi> that is, the Soveraign Magiſtrate, <hi>to whoſe Authority we must stand no leſs, than to theirs, who at firſt did commend the Scripture to us for the Canon of Faith.</hi> Thus if Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Soveraigns, of different Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, do claſh one with another, in their interpretations, or miſinterpretation of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture (as they do daily) then the word of God is contradictory to it ſelf; or that is the word of God in one Common-wealth, which is the word of the Devil in another Common-wealth. And the ſame thing may be true, and not true at the ſame time: Which is the peculiar priviledge of <hi>T.H.</hi> to make Contradictories to be true toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>There is no doubt but by what Authority the Scripture or any other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is made a Law, by the ſame Authority the Scriptures are to be interpreted, or elſe they are made Law in vain. But to obey is one thing, to believe is another; which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction perhaps his Lordſhip never heard of. To obey is to do or forbear as one is commanded, and depends on the Will; but to believe depends not on the Will, but on the providence and guidance of our hearts that are in the hands of God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Laws only require obedience; Belief
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33138:41"/>requires Teachers and Arguments drawn ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from Reaſon, or from ſome thing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready believed. Where there is no reaſon for our Belief, there is no reaſon we ſhould believe. The reaſon why men believe, is drawn from the Authority of thoſe men whom we have no juſt cauſe to miſtruſt, that is, of ſuch men to whom no profit accrues by their deceiving us, and of ſuch men as never uſed to lye, or elſe from the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch men whoſe Promiſes, Threats, and Affirmations we have ſeen confirmed by God with Miracles. If it be not from the Kings Authority that the Scripture is Law, what other Authority makes it Law? Here ſome man being of his Lordſhips judgment will perhaps laugh and ſay, 'tis the Authority of God that makes them Law. I grant that. But my queſtion is, on what Authority they believe that God is the Author of them? Here his Lordſhip would have been at a Nonplus, and turning round, would have ſaid the Authority of the Scripture makes good that God is their Author. If it be ſaid we are to believe the Scripture upon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Univerſal Church, why are not the Books we call Apocrypha the Word of God as well as the reſt? If this Authority be in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> then it is not any other than the Authority of the Head of the Church, which is the King. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33138:41"/>the Head the Church is mute, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority therefore is in the King; which is all that I contended for in this point. As to the Laws of the Gentiles, concerning Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the Primitive times of the Church, I confeſs they were contrary to Chriſtian Faith. But none of their Laws, nor Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, nor a mans own Will are able to take away Faith, though they can compel to an external obedience; and though I may blame the <hi>Ethnick</hi> Princes for compelling men to ſpeak what they thought not, yet I abſolve not all thoſe that have had the Power in Chriſtian Churches from the ſame fault. For I believe ſince the time of the firſt four Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councels, there have been more Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians burnt and killed in the Chriſtian Church by Eccleſiaſtical Authority, than by the Heathen Emperors Laws for Religion on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without Sedition. All that the Biſhop does in this Argument is but a heaving at the Kings Supremacy. Oh, but (ſays he) if two Kings interpret a place of Scripture in contrary ſences, it will follow that both ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are true. It does not follow, For the interpretation, though it be made by juſt Authority, muſt not therefore always be true. If the Doctrine in the one ſence be neceſſary to Salvation, then they that hold the other muſt dye in their ſins, and be Damned. But if the Doctrine in neither
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33138:42"/>ſence be neceſſary to Salvation, then all is well, except perhaps that they will call one another Atheiſts, and fight about it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>All the power, vertue, uſe and efficacy, which he aſcribeth to the Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, is to be <hi>ſigns or commemorations.</hi> As for any ſealing, or confirming, or confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Grace, he acknowledgeth nothing. The ſame he ſaith particularly of Baptiſm: Upon which grounds a Cardinals red Hat, or a Serjeant at Arms his Mace, may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Sacraments as well as Baptiſm, or the holy Euchariſt, if they be only ſigns and commemorations of a benefit. If he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, that Baptiſm and the Euchariſt, are of Divine inſtitution: But a Cardinals red Hat or a Serjeant at Arms his Mace are not: He ſaith truly but nothing to his advantage or purpoſe, ſeeing he deriveth all the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Word and Sacraments, in reſpect of Subjects, and all our obligation to them, from the Authority of the Soveraign Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, without which <hi>theſe words repent, and be Baptized in the name of Jeſus, are but Counſel,</hi> no Command. And ſo a Serjeant at Arms his Mace, and Baptiſm, proceed both from the ſame Authority. And this he ſaith upon this filly ground, <hi>That nothing is a Command, the performance whereof tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to our own benefit.</hi> He might as well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the Ten Commandments to be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33138:42"/>becauſe they have an advantagious promiſe annexed to them, <hi>Do this and thou ſhalt live;</hi> And <hi>Curſed is every one that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth not in all the words of this Law to do them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Of the Sacraments I ſaid no more, than that they are <hi>Signs</hi> or <hi>Commemorations.</hi> He finds fault that I add not <hi>Seals, Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations,</hi> and that they <hi>confer grace.</hi> Firſt, I would have asked him if a Seal be any thing elſe beſides a Sign, whereby to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſomewhat, as that we have promiſed, accepted, acknowledged, given, underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſomewhat. Are not other <hi>Signs</hi> though without a <hi>Seal,</hi> of force ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince me or oblige me? A Writing obligato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or Releaſe ſigned only with a mans name is as Obligatory as a Bond ſigned and ſealed, if it be ſufficiently proved, though perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture it may require a longer Proceſs to obtain a Sentence, but his Lordſhip I think knew better than I do the force of Bonds and Bills; yet I know this that in the Court of Heaven there is no ſuch difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſaying, ſigning, and ſealing, as his Lordſhip ſeemeth here to pretend. I am Baptized for a Commemoration that I have enrolled my ſelf. I take the Sacrament of the Lords Supper to Commemorate that Chriſt's Body was broken, and his Blood ſhed for my redemption. What is there
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33138:43"/>more intimated concerning the nature of theſe Sacraments, either in the Scripture or in the Book of Common-Prayer? Have Bread and Wine and Water in their own Nature, any other Quality than they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Conſecration? It is true that the Conſecration gives theſe bodies a new Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, as being a giving and dedicating of them to God, that is to ſay a making of them Holy, not a changing of their Quality. But as ſome ſilly young men returning from <hi>France</hi> affect a broken <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to be thought perfect in the <hi>French</hi> language; ſo his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (I think) to ſeem a perfect underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the unintelligible language of the Schoolmen, pretends an ignorance of his Mother Tongue. He talks here of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> and <hi>Counſel</hi> as if he were no <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, nor knew any difference between their ſignifications. What <hi>Engliſh</hi> man when he commandeth, ſays more than, Do this; yet he looks to be obeyed, if obedience be due unto him. But when he ſays, <hi>Do this,</hi> and <hi>thou ſhalt have ſuch or ſuch a Reward,</hi> he encourages him, or adviſes him, or Bargains with him, but Commands him not. Oh, the underſtanding of a Schoolman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Sometimes he is for holy Orders, and giveth to the Paſtors of the Church the right of Ordination and Abſolution, and Infallibility, too much for a particular Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33138:43"/>or the Paſtors of one particular Church. <hi>It is manifest, that the conſecration of the chiefest Doctors in every Church, and impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands, doth pertain to the Doctors of the ſame Church.</hi> And <hi>it cannot be doubted of, but the power of binding and looſing was given by Christ to the future Pastors, after the ſame manner as to his preſent Apostles.</hi> And <hi>our Saviour hath promiſed this infallibility in thoſe things which are neceſſary to Salvation, to his Apostles, until the day of Judgment, that is to ſay, to the Apostles and Pastors, to be Conſecrated by the Apoſtles ſucceſſively, by the impoſition of hands.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But at other times he caſteth all this Meal down with his foot. <hi>Chriſtian Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns are the ſupream Pastors, and the only perſons whom Christians now hear ſpeak from God, except ſuch as God ſpeaketh to in theſe dayes ſupernaturally.</hi> What is now become of the promiſed infallibility?</p>
                     <p>And <hi>it is from the Civil Soveraign that all other Paſtors derive their right of teaching, preaching, and all other functions pertaining to that Office, and they are but his Ministers in the ſame manner as the Magiſtrates of Towns, or Judges in Courts of Juſtice, and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Armies.</hi> What is now become of their Ordination? Magiſtrates, Judges, and Generals, need no precedent qualifications. He maketh <hi>the Pastoral Authority of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33138:44"/>to be</hi> Jure divino, <hi>of all other Pastors</hi> Jure civili: He addeth, <hi>neither is there any Judge of Hereſie among Subjects, but their own civil Soveraign.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Laſtly, <hi>the Church Excommunicateth no man but whom ſhe Excommunicateth by the Authority of the Prince.</hi> And <hi>the effect of Excommunication hath nothing in it, neither of dammage in this World, nor terror upon an Apostate, if the Civil Power did perſecute or not aſſist the Church. And in the World to come, leaves them in no worſe estate, than thoſe who never believed. The dammage ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther redoundeth to the Church. Neither is the Excommunication of a Chriſtian Subject, that obeyeth the Laws of his own Soveraign, of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny effect.</hi> Where is now their power of binding and looſing?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Here his Lordſhip condemneth, firſt my too much kindneſs to the Paſtors of the Church; as if I aſcribed Infallibility to every particular Miniſter, or at leaſt to the Aſſembly of the Paſtors of a particular Church. But he miſtakes me, I never meant to flatter them ſo much. I ſay only that the Ceremony of Conſecration, and Impoſition of hands belongs to them; and that alſo no otherwiſe than as given them by the Laws of the Common-wealth. The Biſhop Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates, but the King both makes him Biſhop and gives him his Authority. The Head of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33138:44"/>the Church not only gives the power of Conſecration, Dedication, and Benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but may alſo exerciſe the Act himſelf if he pleaſe. <hi>Solomon</hi> did it, and the Book of Canons ſays, That the King of <hi>England</hi> has all the Right that any good King of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> had. It might have added that any other King or ſoveraign Aſſembly had in their own Dominions. I deny That any Paſtor or any Aſſembly of Paſtors in any particular Church, or all the Churches on earth though united are Infallible. Yet I ſay the Paſtors of a Chriſtian Church aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled are in all ſuch points as are <hi>neceſſary to Salvation.</hi> But about what points are <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation</hi> he and I differ. For I in the 43d <hi>chapter</hi> of my <hi>Leviathan</hi> have proved that this Article, <hi>Jeſus is the Chriſt,</hi> is the <hi>unum neceſſarium, the only Article ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation;</hi> to which his Lordſhip hath not offered any Objection. And he (it ſeems) would have neceſſary to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every Doctrine he himſelf thought ſo. Doubtleſs in this Article, <hi>Jeſus is the Chriſt,</hi> every Church is infallible; for elſe it were no Church. Then he ſays, I overthrow this again by ſaying that Chriſtian Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns are the <hi>Supream Paſtors,</hi> that is, Heads of their own Churches; <hi>That they have their Authority Jure Divino; That all other Pastors have it Jure Civili:</hi> How came
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33138:45"/>any Biſhop to have Authority over me, but by Letters Patents from the King? I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member a Parliament wherein a Biſhop, who was both a good Preacher and a good Man, was blamed for a Book he had a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before Publiſhed in maintenance of the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of Biſhops; a thing which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Reformation here, was never al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them by the Pope. Two <hi>Jus Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinums</hi> cannot ſtand together in one King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. In the laſt place he miſlikes that the Church ſhould Excommunicate by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the King, that is to ſay, by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Head of the Church. But he tells not why. He might as well miſlike that the Magiſtrates of the Realm ſhould execute their Offices by the Authority of the Head of the Realm. His Lordſhip was in a great error, if he thought ſuch incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments would add any thing to the Wealth, Dignity, Reverence or Continuance of his Order. They are Paſtors of Paſtors, but yet they are the Sheep of him that is on earth their ſoveraign Paſtor, and he again a Sheep of that ſupream Paſtor which is in Heaven. And if they did their paſtoral Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, both by Life and Doctrine, as they ought to do, there could never ariſe any dangerous Rebellion in the Land. But if the people ſee once any ambition in their Teachers, they will ſooner learn that, than
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33138:45"/>any other Doctrine; and from Ambition proceeds Rebellion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>It may be ſome of <hi>T. H.</hi> his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples deſire to know what hopes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly joyes they have upon their Maſters Principles. They may hear them without any great contentment, <hi>There is no mention in Scripture, nor ground in reaſon, of the</hi> Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Empyraeum, that is, the Heaven of the Bleſſed, where the Saints ſhall live eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with God. And again, <hi>I have not found any Text that can probably be drawn to prove any Aſcention of the Saints into Heaven, that is to ſay, into any</hi> Coelum Empyraeum. But he concludeth poſitively, that <hi>Salvation ſhall be upon earth, when God ſhall Raign at the coming of Chriſt in Jeruſalem.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>In ſhort, the Kingdom of God is a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c. called alſo <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven, and the Kingdom of Glory.</hi> All the <hi>Hobbians</hi> can hope for, is, to be reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſame condition which <hi>Adam</hi> was in before his fall. So ſaith <hi>T.H.</hi> himſelf, <hi>From whence may be inferred, that the Elect, after the Reſurrection, ſhall be reſtored to the eſtate wherein</hi> Adam <hi>was before he had ſinned: As for the beatifical viſion he defineth it to be a word unintelligible.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T.H.</speaker>
                     <p>This <hi>Coelum Empyraeum</hi> for which he pretendeth ſo much zeal, where is it in the Scripture, where in the Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33138:46"/>Prayer, where in the Canons, where in the Homilies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or in any part of our Religion? What has a Chriſtian to do with ſuch Language? Nor do I remember it in <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> Perhaps it may be in ſome Schoolman or Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator on <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and his Lordſhip makes it in <hi>Engliſh</hi> the <hi>Heaven of the Bleſſed,</hi> as if <hi>Empyraeum</hi> ſignified <hi>That which belongs to the Bleſſed.</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſays better; that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the day of Judgment all that is not Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſhall be Hell. Then for <hi>Beatifical viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> how can any man underſtand it that knows from the Scripture that no man e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw or can ſee God. Perhaps his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip thinks that the happineſs of the Life to come is not real but a Viſion. As for that which I ſay (<hi>Lev. pag.</hi> 345.) I have anſwered to it already.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>But conſidering his other Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, I do not marvel much at his extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance in this point. To what purpoſe ſhould a <hi>Coelum Empyraeum,</hi> or Heaven of the Bleſſed, ſerve in his judgment, who maketh the bleſſed Angels that are the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of that happy Manſion, to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Idols of the brain, that is in plain <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> nothing, or thin, ſubtil, fluid bodies, deſtroying the Angelical nature. <hi>The uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe being the aggregate of all bodies, there is no real part thereof that is not alſo body.</hi>
                        <pb n="85" facs="tcp:33138:46"/>And elſewhere, <hi>Every part of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe is Body, and that which is not Body, is no part of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe. And becauſe the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe is all, that which is no part of it is nothing, and conſequently no where.</hi> How? By this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine he maketh not only the Angels, but God himſelf to be nothing. Neither doth he ſalve it at all by ſuppoſing erroneouſly Angels to be corporeal Spirits, and by at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing the name of incorporeal Spirit to God, <hi>as being a name of more honour, in whom we conſider not what Attribute beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth his nature, which is incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but what beſt expreſſeth our deſire to honour him.</hi> Though we be not able to comprehend perfectly what God is, yet we are able perfectly to comprehend what God is not, that is, he is not imperfect, and therefore he is not finite, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently he is not corporeal. This were a trim way to honour God indeed to honour him with a lye. If this that he ſay here be true, That <hi>every part of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe is a Body, and whatſoever is not a Body is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> Then by this Doctrine, if God be not a Body, God is nothing; not an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporeal Spirit, but <hi>one of the Idols of the Brain,</hi> a meer nothing, though they think they dance under a Net, and have the blind of Gods incomprehenſibility, between them and diſcovery.</p>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:33138:47"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>This of <hi>Incorporeal ſubſtance</hi> he urged before, and there I anſwered it. I wonder he ſo often rolls the ſame ſtone. He is like <hi>Syſiphus</hi> in the Poets Hell, that there rolls a heavy ſtone up a hill, which no ſooner he brings to day-light, then it ſlips down again to the bottom, and ſerves him ſo perpetually. For ſo his Lordſhip rolls this and other queſtions with much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe till they come to the light of Scripture; and then they vaniſh, and he vexing, ſweating, and railing goes to't again, to as little purpoſe as before. From that I ſay of the Univerſe he infers, that I make God to be nothing. But infers it abſurdly. He might indeed have inferr'd that I make him a Corporeal, but yet a pure Spirit. I mean by the Univerſe, the Aggregate of all things that have being in themſelves, and ſo do all men elſe. And becauſe God has a being, it follows that he is either the whole Univerſe, or part of it. Nor does his Lordſhip go about to diſprove it, but only ſeems to wonder at it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>To what purpoſe ſhould a <hi>Coelum Empyraeum</hi> ſerve in his Judgment, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth the immortality of the Soul? <hi>The Doctrine is now, and hath been a long time far otherwiſe; namely, that every man hath eternity of life by nature, in as much as his Soul is immortal.</hi> Who ſuppoſeth that <hi>when
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33138:47"/>a man dyeth, there remaineth nothing of him but his Carkaſe;</hi> who maketh the word <hi>Soul</hi> in holy Scripture to ſignifie always ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Life, or the Living Creature? And expoundeth the caſting of Body and Soul into Hell-fire, to be <hi>the caſting of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Life into Hell-fire.</hi> Who maketh this Orthodox truth, that the Souls of men are Subſtances diſtinct from their Bodies, to be <hi>an error contracted by the contagion of the Demonology of the Greeks, and a window that gives entrance to the dark Doctrine of eternal torments.</hi> Who expoundeth theſe words of <hi>Solomon, [Then ſhall the duſt return to the earth as it was, and the Spirit ſhall return to God that gave it,]</hi> Thus, <hi>God only knows what becomes of a mans Spirit, when he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpireth.</hi> He will not acknowledge that there is a Spirit, or any Subſtance diſtinct from the Body. I wonder what they think doth keep their Bodies from ſtinking.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>He comes here to that which is a great Paradox in School Divinity. The grounds of my opinion are the Canonical Scripture, and the Texts which I cited I muſt again recite, to which I ſhall alſo add ſome others. My Doctrine is this, Firſt, <hi>That the elect in Chriſt from the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment forward, by vertue of Chriſt's Paſſion and Victory over death, ſhall enjoy eternal life, that is, they ſhall be Immortal.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33138:48"/>
                        <hi>that there is no living Soul ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in place from the Body, more than there is a living Body ſeparated from the Soul.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>That the reprobate ſhall be revived to Judgment, and ſhall dye a ſecond death in Torments, which death ſhall be everlaſting.</hi> Now let us conſider what is ſaid to theſe points in the Scripture, and what is the harmony therein of the Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</p>
                     <p>And firſt, becauſe the word <hi>Immortal Soul,</hi> is not found in the Scriptures, the queſtion is to be decided by evident conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences from the Scripture. The Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſaith of God expreſly (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16.) That <hi>He only hath immortality, and dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in inacceſſible light.</hi> Hence it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the Soul of man is not of its own nature Immortal, but by Grace, that is to ſay, by the gift of God. And then the queſtion will be whether this grace or gift of God were beſtowed on the Soul in the Creation and Conception of the Man, or afterwards by his redemption. Another queſtion will be in what ſence immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Torments can be called a gift, when all gifts ſuppoſe the thing given to be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the receiver. To the firſt of theſe, Chriſt himſelf ſaith (<hi>Luke</hi> 14.13, 14.) <hi>When thou makeſt a Feaſt, call the Poor, the Maimed, the Lame, the Blind, and thou ſhalt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33138:48"/>be Bleſſed, for they cannot recompenſe thee; For thou ſhalt be recompenſed at the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of them that be juſt.</hi> It follows hence that the reward of the Elect is not before the Reſurrection. What reward then en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyes a ſeparated Soul in Heaven, or any where elſe till that day come, or what has he to do there till the Body riſe again? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays (<hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6, 7.) <hi>God will render to every man according to his works. To them who by patient continuance in well doing, ſeek for Honour, Glory and Immortality, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life. But unto them that be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and do not obey the truth, but obey un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, indignation and wrath.</hi> Here it is plain that God gives Eternal Life on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to well doers, and to them that ſeek (not to them that have already) Immortality. Again (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10.) <hi>Chriſt hath aboliſhed Death, and brought Life and Immortality to light, through the Goſpel.</hi> Therefore before the Goſpel of Chriſt, nothing was Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal but God. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of the day of Judgment (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.54.) ſaith that <hi>This Mortal ſhall put on Immortality,</hi> and <hi>that then Death is ſwallowed in Victory.</hi> There was no Immortality of any thing Mortal till Death was overcome, and that was at the Reſurrection. <hi>And John</hi> 8.52. <hi>Verily, Verily, if a man keep my ſayings he ſhall never ſee Death,</hi> that is to ſay, he ſhall
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33138:49"/>be Immortal; but it is no where ſaid, that he which keeps not Chriſt's ſayings ſhall never ſee Death, nor be Immortal, and yet they that ſay that the wicked, Body and Soul, ſhall be tormented everlaſtingly, do therein ſay they are Immortal. Mat. 10.28. <hi>Fear not them that can kill the Body, but are not able to kill the Soul; but fear him that is able to deſtroy both Soul and Body in Hell.</hi> Man cannot kill a Soul, for the Man kill'd ſhall revive again. But God can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Soul and Body in Hell, as that it ſhall never return to life. In the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament we read (<hi>Gen.</hi> 7.4.) I will deſtroy every living Subſtance that I have made from off the face of the Earth; therefore, if the Souls of them that periſhed in the Flood were Subſtances, they were alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed in the Flood and were not Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. (<hi>Math.</hi> 25.41.) <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> Theſe words are to be ſpoken in the day of Judgment, which Judgment is to be in the Clouds. And there ſhall ſtand the men that are reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alive, where Souls according to his Lordſhips Doctrine were ſent long before to Hell. Therefore at that preſent day of Judgment they had one Soul by which they were there alive, and another Soul in Hell. How his Lordſhip could have maintained
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33138:49"/>this, I underſtand not. But by my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, that the Soul is not a ſeparated Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but that the Man at his Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall be revived by God, and raiſed to Judgment, and afterwards Body and Soul deſtroyed in Hell-fire (which is the ſecond death) there is no ſuch conſequence or dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty to be inferred. Beſides it avoids the unneceſſary diſputes about where the Soul of <hi>Lazarus</hi> was for four dayes he lay dead. And the order of the Divine Proceſs is made good, of not inflicting torments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Condemnation pronounced.</p>
                     <p>Now as to the harmony of the two Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments, it is ſaid in the old (<hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17.) <hi>In the day that thou eateſt of the Tree of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, dying thou ſhalt dye. Moriendo mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eris,</hi> that is, when thou art dead thou ſhalt not revive; for ſo hath <hi>Athanaſius</hi> expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it. Therefore <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were not Immortal by their Creation. Then (<hi>Gen.</hi> 3.22.) <hi>Behold the man is become as one of us—Now leſt he put forth his hand and take alſo of the Tree of Life, and eat, and live for ever, &amp;c.</hi> Here they had had an Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity by the gift of God, if they had not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. It was therefore ſin that loſt them Eternal-life. He therefore that redeemed them from ſin was the Author of their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, and conſequently began in the day of Judgment when <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33138:50"/>again made alive by admiſſion to the new Tree of Life, which was Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>Now let us compare this with the New Teſtament. Where we find theſe words (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21.) <hi>ſince by Man came Death, by Man came alſo the Reſurrection of the dead.</hi> Therefore all the Immortality of the Soul, that ſhall be after the Reſurrection, is by Chriſt, and not by the nature of the Soul. verſe 22. <hi>As by Adam all dye, even ſo in Chriſt ſhall all be made alive.</hi> Therefore ſince we dyed by <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin, ſo we ſhall live by Chriſt's Redemption of us, that is, after the Reſurrection. Again verſe 23. <hi>But every man in his order; Chriſt the firſt Fruits, afterwards they that are Chriſts, at his coming.</hi> Therefore none ſhall be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live till the coming of Chriſt. Laſtly, as when God had ſaid, That day that thou eateſt of the Tree of Knowledg of Good and Evil, thou ſhalt dye, though he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned him then, yet he ſuffered him to live a long time after; ſo when Chriſt had ſaid to the Thief on the Croſs, this day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe, yet he ſuffered him to lye dead till the General Reſurrection, for no man roſe again from the dead before our Saviours coming, and conquering death.</p>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:33138:50"/>
                     <p>If God beſtowed Immortality on every man then when he made him, and he made many to whom he never purpoſed to give his ſaving Grace, what did his Lordſhip think that God gave any man Immortality with purpoſe only to make him capable of Immortal Torments? 'Tis a hard ſaying, and I think cannot piouſly be believed. I am ſure it can never be proved by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Scripture.</p>
                     <p>But though I have made it clear that it cannot be drawn by lawful conſequence from Scripture, that Man was Created with a Soul Immortal, and that the Elect only, by the Grace of God in Chriſt, ſhall both Bodies and Souls from the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on forward be Immortal; yet there may be a Conſequence well drawn from ſome words in the Rites of Burial, that prove the contrary, as theſe. <hi>Foraſmuch as it hath pleaſed Abmighty God of his great mercy, to take unto himſelf the Soul of our dear Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther here departed,</hi> &amp;c. And theſe, <hi>Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, with whom do live the Spirits of them that depart hence in the Lord.</hi> Which are words Authoriſed by the Church. I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Lordſhip that had ſo often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced them, took no notice of them here. But it often happens that men think of thoſe things leaſt, which they have moſt perfectly learnt by rote. I am ſorry
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33138:51"/>I could not without deſerting the ſence of Scripture and mine own Conſcience ſay the ſame. But I ſee no juſt cauſe yet why the Church ſhould be offended at it. For the Church of <hi>England</hi> pretendeth not (as doth the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) to be above the Scripture; nor forbiddeth any man to Read the Scripture; nor was I forbidden when I Wrote my <hi>Leviathan</hi> to Publiſh any thing which the Scriptures ſuggeſted. For when I Wrote it, I may ſafely ſay there was no lawful Church in <hi>England,</hi> that could have maintained me in, or prohibited me from Writing any thing. There was no Biſhop, and though there were Preaching, ſuch as it was, yet no Common-Prayer. For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary Prayer, though made in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, is not Common-Prayer. There was then no Church in <hi>England,</hi> that any man living was bound to obey. What I Write here at this preſent time I am forced to in my defence, not againſt the Church, but againſt the accuſations and arguments o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> my Adverſaries. For the Church, though it excommunicates for ſcandalous life, and for teaching falſe Doctrines, yet it profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to impoſe nothing to be held as Faith but what may be warranted by Scripture and this the Church it ſelf ſaith in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 20th of the 39 Articles of Religion. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> therefore I am permitted to alledge Scr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33138:51"/>at any time in the defence of my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>But they that in one caſe are griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in another muſt be relieved. If per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance <hi>T. H.</hi> hath given his Diſciples any diſcontent in his Doctrine of <hi>Heaven</hi> and the <hi>holy</hi> Angels, and <hi>the glorified Souls of the Saints,</hi> he will make them amends in his Doctrine of <hi>Hell,</hi> and the <hi>Devils,</hi> and the <hi>damned Spirits.</hi> Firſt of the Devils; He fancieth that all thoſe Devils which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour did caſt out, were Phrenſies, and all <hi>Demoniacks</hi> (or Perſons poſſeſſed) <hi>no other than Mad-men.</hi> And to juſtifie <hi>our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's ſpeaking to a Diſeaſe as to a Perſon,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the example of inchanters. But he declareth himſelf moſt clearly upon this Subject, in his Animadverſions upon my reply to his defence of fatal deſtiny. <hi>There are in the Scripture two ſorts of things which are in</hi> Engliſh <hi>tranſlated Devils.</hi> One is <hi>that which is called</hi> Satan, Diabolus, Abaddon, <hi>which ſignifieth in</hi> Engliſh <hi>an Enemy, an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer, and a deſtroyer of the Church of God, in which ſence the Devils are but wicked men. The other ſort of Devils are called in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> Daemonia, <hi>which are the feigned Gods of the Heathen, and are neither Bodies nor ſpiritual Subſtances, but meer fancies, and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of terrified hearts, feigned by the</hi> Greeks, <hi>and other Heathen People, which St.</hi> Paul
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:33138:52"/>
                        <hi>calleth Nothings.</hi> So <hi>T.H.</hi> hath killed the great infernal Devil, and all his black An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and left no Devils to be feared, but Devils Incarnate, that is, wicked men.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>As for the firſt words cited (<hi>Levi. page</hi> 38, 39.) I refer the Reader to the place it ſelf; and for the words concerning Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, I leave them to the judgment of the Learned.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>And for <hi>Hell</hi> he deſcribeth the <hi>Kingdom of Satan,</hi> or the <hi>Kingdom of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> to be <hi>a confederacy of deceivers.</hi> He telleth us that the places which ſet forth the torments of Hell in holy Scripture, <hi>do deſign Metaphorically a grief and diſcontent of mind, from the ſight of that eternal felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in others, which they themſelves, through their own incredulity and diſobedience have loſt.</hi> As if Metaphorical deſcriptions did not bear ſad truths in them, as well as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teral, as if final deſperation were no more than a little fit of grief or diſcontent; and a guilty conſcience were no more than a tranſitory paſſion, as if it were a loſs ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily to be born, to be deprived for evermore of the beatifical Viſion: and laſtly as if the Damned, beſides that unſpeakable loſs, did not likewiſe ſuffer actual Torments, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable in ſome meaſure to their own ſins, and Gods Juſtice.</p>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:33138:52"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>That Metaphors bear ſad truths in them, I deny not. It is a ſad thing to loſe this preſent life untimely. Is it not therefore much more a ſad thing to loſe an eternal happy Life? And I believe that he which will venture upon ſin, with ſuch danger, will not ſtick to do the ſame not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Doctrine of eternal tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Is it not alſo a ſad truth, that the Kingdom of darkneſs ſhould be a Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy of deceivers?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Laſtly, for the damned Spirits, he declareth himſelf every where, that their ſufferings are not eternal. <hi>The Fire ſhall be unquenchable, and the Torments everlaſting; but it cannot be thence inferred, that he who ſhall be caſt into that Fire, or be tormented with thoſe Torments, ſhall endure and reſiſt them, ſo as to be eternally burnt and tortured, and yet never be deſtroyed nor dye. And though there be many places, that affirm ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire, into which men may be caſt ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſivily one after another for ever; yet I find none that affirm that there ſhall be an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life therein of any individual Perſon.</hi> If he had ſaid, and ſaid only, that the pains of the Damned may be leſſened, as to the degree of them, or that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure not for ever, but that after they are purged by long torments from their droſs and Corruptions, as Gold in the fire, both
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:33138:53"/>the damned Spirits and the Devils them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhould be reſtored to a better condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he might have found ſome Ancients (who are therefore called <hi>the merciful Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi>) to have joyned with him, though ſtill he ſhould have wanted the ſuffrage of the Catholick Church.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Why does not his Lordſhip cite ſome place of Scripture here to prove that all the Reprobates which are dead, live e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternally in torment? We read indeed That everlaſting Torments were prepared for the Devil and his Angels, whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alſo are everlaſting; and that the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and the <hi>falſe Prophet</hi> ſhall be torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed everlaſtingly; but not that every Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate ſhall be ſo. They ſhall indeed be caſt into the ſame fire, but the Scripture ſays plainly enough, that they ſhall be both Body and Soul deſtroyed there. If I had ſaid that the Devils themſelves ſhould be reſtored to a better condition; his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip would have been ſo kind as to have put me into the number of the <hi>Merciful Doctors.</hi> Truly if I had had any Warrant for the poſſibility of their being leſs ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Church of God than they have been, I would have been as merciful to them as any Doctor of them all. As it is, I am more merciful than the Biſhop.</p>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:33138:53"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>But his ſhooting is not at rovers, but altogether at randome, without either Preſident or Partner. All that <hi>eternal ſire,</hi> all thoſe torments which he acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, is but this, That <hi>after the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the Reprobate ſhall be in the eſtate that</hi> Adam <hi>and his Poſterity were in, after the ſin committed, ſaving that God promiſed a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer to</hi> Adam <hi>and not to them.</hi> Adding, <hi>that they ſhall live as they did</hi> formerly, <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and give in Marriage; and conſequently engender</hi> Children <hi>perpetually after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, as they did before,</hi> which he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>an immortallity of the kind, but not of the perſons of men.</hi> It is to be preſumed, that in thoſe their ſecond lives, knowing certainly from <hi>T. H.</hi> that there is no hope of Redemption for them from corporal death upon their well-doing; nor fear of any Torments after death for their ill-doing, they will paſs their times here as pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as they can. This is all the Damnation which <hi>T. H.</hi> fancieth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>This he has urged once before, and I anſwered to it, That the whole Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph was to prove, that for any Text of Scripture to the contrary, men might, after the Reſurrection live as <hi>Adam</hi> did on earth, and that notwithſtanding the Text of St. <hi>Luke chap.</hi> 20. <hi>verſe</hi> 34, 35, 36. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and propagate.</hi> But that they ſhall do ſo,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:33138:54"/>is no aſſertion of mine. His Lordſhip knew I held that after the Reſurrection there ſhall be at all no wicked men; but the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect (all that are, have been, and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall be) ſhall live on earth. But St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſays, there ſhall then be a new Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and a new Earth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>In ſumm I leave it to the free judgment of the underſtanding Reader, by theſe few inſtances which follow, to judge what the <hi>Hobbian</hi> Principles are in point of Religion. <hi>Ex ungue leonem.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Firſt, that no man needs to put himſelf to any hazzard for his Faith, but may ſafely comply with the times. <hi>And for their Faith it is internal and inviſible. They have the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence that</hi> Naaman <hi>had, and need not put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into danger for it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, he alloweth Subjects, being commanded by their Soveraign, to deny Chriſt. <hi>Profeſſion with the Tongue is but an external thing, and no more than any other ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, whereby we ſignifie our obedience. And wherein a Chriſtian, holding firmly in his heart the Faith of Chriſt, hath the ſame liberty which the Prophet</hi> Eliſha <hi>allowed to</hi> Naaman &amp;c. <hi>Who by bowing before the Idol</hi> Rimmon <hi>denyed the true God as much in effect, as if he had done it with his Lips.</hi> Alas, why did St. <hi>Peter</hi> Weep ſo bitterly for denying his Maſter, out of fear of his Life or Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers?
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:33138:54"/>It ſeems he was not acquainted with theſe <hi>Hobbian</hi> Principles. And in the ſame place he layeth down this general Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. <hi>This we may ſay that whatſoever a Subject is compelled to, in obedience to his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, and doth it not in order to his own mind, but in order to the Laws of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, that action is not his, but his Soveraign's; nor is it he that in this caſe denyeth Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, but his Governor and the Law of his Country.</hi> His inſtance in a <hi>Mahometan</hi> commanded by a Chriſtian Prince to be preſent at Divine Service, is a weak mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, ſpringing from his groſs ignorance in Caſe-Divinity, not knowing to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between an erroneous Conſcience, as the <hi>Mahometans</hi> is, and a Conſcience right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>In theſe his two firſt inſtances I confeſs his Lordſhip does not much belye me. But neither does he confute me. Alſo I confeſs my ignorance in his Caſe-Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is grounded upon the Doctrine of the School-men. Who to decide Caſes of Conſcience, take in, not only the Scriptures, but alſo the Decrees of the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> for the advancing of the Dominion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church over Conſciences; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the true deciſion of Caſes of Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ought to be grounded only on Scripture, or natural Equity. I never allowed the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:33138:55"/>denying of Chriſt with the Tongue in all men, but expreſly ſay the contrary (<hi>Lev. pag.</hi> 362.) in theſe words, For an unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man that is in the power of an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous King or State, if commanded on pain of death to worſhip before an Idol, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth the Idol in his heart; he doth well, though if he had the fortitude to ſuffer death rather than worſhip it, he ſhould do better. But if a Paſtor who as Chriſt's meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger has undertaken to teach Chriſt's Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to all Nations, ſhould do the ſame, it were not only a ſinful ſcandal in reſpect of other Chriſtian mens Conſciences, but a perſidious forſaking of his charge. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Peter</hi> in denying Chriſt ſinned, as being an Apoſtle. And 'tis ſin in every man that ſhould now take upon him to preach againſt the power of the Pope, to leave his Commiſſion unexecuted for fear of the fire; but in a meer Traveller, not ſo. The three Children and <hi>Daniel</hi> were worthy Champions of the true Religion. But God requireth not of every man to be a Champion. As for his Lordſhip's words of <hi>complying with the times,</hi> they are not mine, but his own ſpightful Paraphraſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Thirdly, if this be not enough, he giveth licence to a Chriſtian to commit Idolatry, or at leaſt to do an Idolatrous act, for fear of death or corporal danger. <hi>To
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:33138:55"/>pray unto a King voluntarily for fair weather, or for any thing which God only can do for us, is divine Worſhip, and Idolatry. On the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, if a King compel a man to it by the terror of death, or other great corporal puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is not Idolatry.</hi> His reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>it is not a ſign, that he doth inwardly honour him as a God, but that he is deſirous to ſave himſelf from death, or from a miſerable life.</hi> If ſeemeth <hi>T. H.</hi> thinketh there is no divine Worſhip, but internal. And that it is lawful for a man to value his own life or his limbs more than his God. How much is he wiſer than the three Children, or <hi>Daniel</hi> himſelf? who were thrown, the firſt into a fiery Furnace, the laſt into the Lions Denn, becauſe they refuſed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the Idolatrous Decree of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Prince.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Here alſo my words are truly ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But his Lordſhip underſtood not what the word <hi>Worſhip</hi> ſignifies; and yet he knew what I meant by it. To think high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of God (as I had defined it) is to honour him. But <hi>to think</hi> is internal. To Worſhip, is to ſignifie that Honour which we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly give, by ſigns <hi>external.</hi> This un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood (as by his Lordſhip it was) all he ſays to it is but a cavil.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>A fourth Aphoriſm may be this, <hi>That which is ſaid in the Scripture, it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:33138:56"/>to obey God than man, hath place in the Kingdom of God by Pact, and not by Nature.</hi> Why? Nature it ſelf doth teach us it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to obey God than men. Neither can he ſay that he intended this only of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in the uſe of indifferent actions and geſtures, in the ſervice of God, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Common-wealth, for that is to obey both God and man. But if divine Law and humane Law claſh one with another, without doubt it is evermore better to obey God than man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Here again appears his unskilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in reaſoning. Who denyes, but it is alwayes, and in all cauſes better to obey God than Man? But there is no Law, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther divine nor humane that ought to be taken for a Law, till we know what it is, and if a divine Law, till we, know that God hath commanded it to be kept. We agree that the Scriptures are the Word of God. But they are a Law by Pact. that is, to us who have been Baptized into the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. To all others it is an invitation only to their own benefit. 'Tis true that even nature ſuggeſteth to us that the Law of God is to be obeyed rather than the Law of man. But nature does not ſuggeſt to us that the Scripture is the Law of God, much leſs how every Text of it ought to be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. But who then ſhall ſuggeſt this? Dr.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:33138:56"/>
                        <hi>Bramhall?</hi> I deny it. Who then? The ſtream of Divines? Why ſo? Am I that have the Scripture it ſelf before my eyes, obliged to venture my eternal life upon their interpretation, how learned ſoever they pretend to be, when no counter-ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity that they can give me, will ſave me harmleſs? If not the ſtream of Divines, who then? The lawful Aſſembly of Paſtors or of Biſhops? But there can be no lawful Aſſembly in <hi>England</hi> without the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the King. The Scripture therefore what it is, and how to be interpreted, is made known unto us here, by no other way than the Authority of our Soveraign Lord both in Temporals and Spirituals, The Kings Majeſty. And where he has ſet forth no Interpretation, there I am allowed to follow my own, as well as any other man, Biſhop or not Biſhop. For my own part, all that know me, know alſo it is my opinion, That the beſt government in Religion is by E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy, but in the King's Right, not in their own. But my Lord of <hi>Derry</hi> not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with this, would have the utmoſt reſolution of our Faith to be into the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Schools. I do not think that all the Biſhops be of his mind. If they were, I would wiſh them to ſtand in fear of that dreadful Sentence, <hi>All covet all loſe.</hi> I muſt not let paſs theſe words of his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33138:57"/>
                        <hi>If divine Law and humane Law claſh one with another, without doubt it is better evermore to obey God than man.</hi> Where the King is a Chriſtian, believes the Scripture, and hath the Legiſlative power both in Church and State, and maketh no Laws concerning Chriſtian Faith, or divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but by the Counſel of his Biſhops whom he truſteth in that behalf, if the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops counſel him aright, what claſhing can there be between the divine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws? For if the Civil Law be againſt God's Law, and the Biſhops make it clearly appear to the King that it claſheth with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Law, no doubt he will mend it by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or by the advice of his Parliament; for elſe he is no profeſſor of Chriſt's Doctrine, and ſo the claſhing is at an end. But if they think that every opinion they hold, though obſcure and unneceſſary to Salvation, ought preſently to be Law, then there will be cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhings innumerable, not only of Laws, but alſo of Swords, as we have found it too true by late experience. But his Lordſhip is ſtill at this, that there ought to be, for the divine Laws that is to ſay, for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of Scripture, a Legiſlative pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Church, diſtinct from that of the King, which under him they enjoy already. This I deny. Then for claſhing between the Civil Laws of Indels with the Law of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33138:57"/>God, the Apoſtles teach that thoſe their Civil Laws are to be obeyed, but ſo as to keep their Faith in Chriſt entirely in their hearts; which is an obedience eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. But I do not believe that <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> or <hi>Nero</hi> was bound to make the holy Scripture Law; and yet unleſs they did ſo they could not attain to eternal life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>His fifth concluſion may be, that the ſharpeſt and moſt ſuccesful Sword, in any War whatſoever, doth give Soveraign Power and Authority to him that hath it, to approve or reject all ſorts of Theological Doctrines, concerning the Kingdom of God, not according to their truth or falſhood, but according to that influence which they have upon political affairs. Hear him, <hi>But becauſe this Doctrine will appear to moſt men a novelty, I do but propound it, maintaining nothing in this or any other Paradox of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but attending the end of that diſpute of the Sword, concerning the Authority (not yet amongſt my Country-men decided) by which all ſorts of Doctrine are to be approved or reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For, the points of Doctrine concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Kingdom of God, have ſo great influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the Kingdom of Man, as not to be determined, but by them that under God have the Soveraign Power.</hi>
                        <q>
                           <l>—Careat ſucceſſibus opto,</l>
                           <l>Quiſquis ab eventu facta notanda putat.</l>
                        </q>
                        <pb n="108" facs="tcp:33138:58"/>Let him evermore want ſucceſs who think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth actions are to be judged by their events. This Doctrine may be plauſible to thoſe who deſire to fiſh in troubled Waters. But it is juſtly hated by thoſe which are in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and all thoſe who are lovers of peace and tranquillity.</p>
                     <p>The laſt part of this concluſion ſmelleth rankly of Jeroboam, <hi>Now ſhall the Kingdom return to the houſe of</hi> David, <hi>if this people go up to do Sacrifice in the houſe of the Lord at</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>whereupon the King took counſel, and made two Calves of Gold, and ſaid unto them, It is too much for you to go up to</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>behold thy Gods O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>which brought thee out of the Land of Aegypt.</hi> But by the juſt diſpoſition of Almighty. God this Policy turned to a ſin, and was the utter deſtruction of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and his Family. It is not good jeſting with edge-tools, nor playing with holy things: Where men make their greateſt faſtneſs, many times they find moſt danger.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>His Lordſhip either had a ſtrange Conſcience, or underſtood not <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Paris</hi> when there was no Biſhop nor Church in <hi>England,</hi> and every man writ what he pleaſed, I reſolved (when it ſhould pleaſe God to reſtore the Authority Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical) to ſubmit to that Authority, in whatſoever it ſhould determine. This his
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:33138:58"/>Lordſhip conſtrues for a temporizing and too much indifferency in Religion; and ſays further that the laſt part of my words do ſmell of <hi>Jeroboam.</hi> To the contrary I ſay my words were modeſt, and ſuch as in duty I ought to uſe. And I profeſs ſtill that whatſoever the Church of <hi>England</hi> (the Church, I ſay, not every Doctor) ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid me to ſay in matter of Faith, I ſhall abſtain from ſaying it, excepting this point. That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God dyed for my ſins.</hi> As for other Doctrins, I think it unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful if the Church define them for any Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church to contradict them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>His ſixth Paradox is a rapper, <hi>the Civil Laws are the Rules of good and evil, juſt and unjuſt, honeſt and diſhoneſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what the Lawgiver commands that is to be accounted good, what he forbids bad.</hi> And a little after, <hi>before Empires were, juſt and unjuſt were not, as whoſe nature is Relative to a Command, every action in its own nature is indifferent. That it is juſt or unjuſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the right of him that command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. Therefore lawful Kings make thoſe things which they command, Juſt by commanding them, and thoſe things which they forbid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt by forbidding them.</hi> To this add his definition of a ſin, <hi>that which one doth, or omitteth, ſaith, or willeth contrary to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Common-wealth, that is, the [Civil]
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:33138:59"/>Laws.</hi> Where by the Laws he doth not underſtand the Written Laws, elected and approved by the whole Common-wealth, but the verbal Commands or Mandates, of him that hath the Soveraign Power, as we find in many places of his Writings. <hi>The Civil Laws are nothing elſe but the Commands of him, that is endowed with Soveraign Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the Common-wealth, concerning the future actions of his Subjects. And the Civil Laws are faſtned to the Lips of that man who hath the Soveraign Power.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Where are we? In <hi>Europe</hi> or in <hi>Aſia?</hi> Where they aſcribed a Divinity to their Kings, and, to uſe his own Phraſe, made them <hi>Mortal Gods. O King live for ever.</hi> Flatterers are the common Moths of great Pallaces, where <hi>Alexander</hi>'s friends are more numerous than the King's friends. But ſuch groſs palpable pernicious flattery as this is, I did never meet with, ſo derogatory both to piety and policy. What deſerved he who ſhould do his uttermoſt endeavour to poyſon a common Fountain, whereof all the Common-wealth muſt drink? He doth the ſame who poiſoneth the mind of a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Prince.</p>
                     <p>Are <hi>the Civil Laws the Rules of good and bad, juſt and unjuſt, honeſt and diſhoneſt?</hi> And what I pray your are the Rules of the Civil Law it ſelf? Even the Law of God
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33138:59"/>and Nature. If the Civil Laws ſwerve from theſe more authentick Laws, they are Lesbian Rules. <hi>What the Lawgiver com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands is to be accounted good, what he forbids bad.</hi> This was juſt the garb of the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Sophiſters, as they are deſcribed by <hi>Plato.</hi> Whatſoever pleaſed the great Beaſt [the Multitude] they call holy, and juſt, and good. And whatſoever the great Beaſt diſliked, they called evil, unjuſt, prophane. But he is not yet arrived at the height of his flattery. <hi>Lawful Kings make thoſe things which they command juſt by commanding them.</hi> At other times when he is in his right wits he talketh of ſufferings, and <hi>expecting their reward in Heaven. And going to Chriſt by Martyrdome. And if he had the fortitude to ſuffer death he ſhould do better.</hi> But I fear all this was but ſaid in jeſt. How ſhould they expect their reward in Heaven, if his Doctrine be true, that there is no reward in Heaven? Or how ſhould they be Martyrs, if his Doctrine betrue, that <hi>none can be Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs but thoſe who converſed with Chriſt upon earth?</hi> He addeth, <hi>Before Empires were, juſt and unjuſt were not.</hi> Nothing could be written more falſe in his ſence, more diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, more inglorious to the humane nature. That God ſhould create Man and leave him preſently without any Rules, to his own ordering of himſelf, as the Oſtridg leaveth her Eggs in the ſand. But in truth
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:33138:60"/>there have been Empires in the World e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince <hi>Adam.</hi> And <hi>Adam</hi> had a Law written in his heart by the finger of God, before there was any Civil Law. Thus they do endeavour to make goodneſs, and juſtice, and honeſty, and conſcience, and God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to be empty names, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, which ſignifie nothing, further than they conduce to a man's intereſt. Otherwiſe he would not, he could not ſay, That <hi>every action as it is inveſted with its circumſtances, is indifferent in its own nature.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>My ſixth Paradox he calls a Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. A Rapper, a Swapper and ſuch like terms are his Lordſhips elegancies. But let us ſee what this Rapper is. 'Tis this, The Civil Laws are the Rules of Good and Evil, Juſt and Unjuſt, Honeſt and Diſhon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. Truly I ſee no other Rules they have. The Scriptures themſelves were made Law to us here, by the Authority of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and are therefore part of the Law Civil. If they were Laws in their own nature, then were they Laws over all the World, and men were obliged to obey them in <hi>America,</hi> as ſoon as they ſhould be ſhown there (though without a Miracle) by a Frier. What is Injuſt but the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of a Law? <hi>Law</hi> therefore was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Unjuſt. And the Law was made known by Soveraign Power before it was a Law. Therefore <hi>Soveraign Power</hi> was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:33138:60"/>both to <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Injuſtice.</hi> Who then made Injuſt but Soveraign Kings or Soveraign Aſtemblies? Where is now the wonder of this Rapper, <hi>That Lawful Kings make thoſe things which they command Just by commanding them, and thoſe things which they forbid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njust by forbidding them?</hi> Juſt and Unjuſt were ſurely made; if the King made them not, who made them elſe? For certainly the breach of a Civil Law is a ſin againſt God. Another Calumny which he would fix upon me, is, That I make the King's verbal Commands to be Laws. How ſo? Becauſe I ſay <hi>the Civil Laws are nothing elſe but the Commands of him that hath the Soveraign Power, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the future Actions of his Subjects.</hi> What verbal Command of a King can arrive at the ears of all his Subjects (which it muſt do ere it be a Law) without the Seal of the Perſon of the Common-wealth (which is here the Great Seal of <hi>England?</hi>) Who but his Lordſhip ever denyed that the command of <hi>England</hi> was a Law to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> men? Or that any but the King had Authority to affix the Great Seal of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to any Writing? And who did ever doubt to call our Laws (though made in Parliament) the King's Laws? What was ever called a Law which the King did not aſſent to? Becauſe the King has granted in
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:33138:61"/>divers caſes not to make a Law without the advice and aſſent of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, therefore when there is no Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in being, ſhall the Great Seal of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> ſtand for nothing? What was more unjuſtly maintained during the long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (beſides the reſiſting and Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the King) then this Doctrine of his Lordſhip's? But the Biſhop endeavoured here to make the Multitude believe I main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, That the King ſinneth not though he bid hang a man for making his Apparel o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than he appointed, or his Servant for negligent attendance. And yet he knew I diſtinguiſhed always between the King's natural and politick capacity. What name ſhould I give to this wilful ſlander? But here his Lordſhip enters into paſſion, and exclaims, <hi>Where are we, in</hi> Europe <hi>or in</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia? <hi>Groſs, palpable, pernicious flattery, poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning of a Common-wealth, poyſoning the King's mind.</hi> But where was his Lordſhip when he wrote this? One would not think he was in <hi>France,</hi> nor that this Doctrine was Written in the year 1658, but rather in the year 1648, in ſome Cabal of the King's enemies. But what did put him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this fit of Choller? Partly, this very thing, that he could not anſwer my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but chiefly, that he had loſt upon me ſo much School-learning in our contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33138:61"/>touching <hi>Liberty and Neceſſity,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was to blame himſelf, for believing that the obſcure and barbarous Language of School Divinity could ſatisfie an ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reader as well as plain and perſpicuous <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Do I flatter the King? Why am I not rich? I confeſs his Lordſhip has not flattered him here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>Something there is which he hath a confuſed glimmering of, as the blind man ſees <hi>men walking like Trees,</hi> which he is not able to apprehend and expreſs clearly. We acknowledge, that though the Laws or Commands of a Soveraign Prince be erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, or unjuſt, or injurious, ſuch as a Subject cannot approve for good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; yet he is bound to acquieſce, and may not oppoſe or reſiſt, otherwiſe than by Prayers and Tears, and at the moſt by flight. We acknowledge that the Civil Laws have power to bind the Conſcience of a Chriſtian, in themſelves, but not from themſelves, but from him who hath ſaid, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher Powers.</hi> Either they bind Chriſtian Subjects to do their Soveraign's Commands, or to ſuffer for the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience. We acknowledge that in doubtful Caſes <hi>ſemper praeſumitur pro Rege &amp; Lege,</hi> the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign and the Law are always preſumed to be in the right. But in plain evident ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:33138:62"/>which admit no doubt, it is always bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to obey God than man. Blunderers whilſt they think to mend one imaginary hole, make two or three real ones. They who derive the Authority of the Scriptures or God's Law from the Civil Laws of men, are like thoſe who ſeek to underprop the Heavens from falling with a Bullruſh. Nay, they derive not only the Authority of the Scripture, but even the Law of nature it ſelf from the Civil Law. <hi>The Laws of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (which need no promulgation) <hi>in the condition of nature are not properly Laws, but qualities which diſpoſe men to peace and obedience. When a Common-wealth is once ſetled, then are they actually Laws and not before.</hi> God help us, into what times are we fallen, when the immutable Laws of God and Nature are made to depend upon the mutable Laws of mortal men, juſt as one ſhould go about to controll the Sun by the Authority of the Clock.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Hitherto he never offered to mend any of the Doctrines he inveighs againſt; but here he does. He ſays I have a glim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mering of ſomething I was not able to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend and expreſs clearly. Let us ſee his Lordſhip's more clear expreſſion. <hi>We ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that though the Laws or Commands of a Soveraign Prince be erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, or unjust, or injurious, ſuch as a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:33138:62"/>cannot approve for good in themſelves, yet he is bound to acquieſce, and may not oppoſe or reſist otherwiſe than by Prayers and Tears, and at the moſt by Flight.</hi> Hence it follows clearly, that when a Soveraign has made a Law, though erroneous, then if his Subject oppoſe it, it is a ſin. Therefore I would fain know, when a man has broken that Law by doing what it forbad, or by refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to do what it commanded, whether he have oppoſed this Law or not. If to break the Law be to oppoſe it, he grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it. Therefore his Lordſhip has not here expreſſed himſelf, ſo clearly as to make men underſtand the difference between breaking a Law and oppoſing it. Though there be ſome difference between breaking of a Law, and oppoſing thoſe that are ſent with force to ſee it executed; yet between breaking and oppoſing the Law it ſelf there is no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference. Alſo though the Subject think the Law juſt, as when a Thief is by Law Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to dye, yet he may lawfully op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Execution, not only by Prayers, Tears and Flight, but alſo (as I think) any way he can. For though his fault were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great, yet his endeavour to ſave his own life is not a fault. For the Law expects it, and for that cauſe appointeth Felons to be carryed bound and encompaſſed with Armed men to Execution. Nothing is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:33138:63"/>to Law but ſin. Nothing oppoſite to the Sheriff but force. So that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's ſight was not ſharp enough to ſee the difference between the Law and the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer. Again, <hi>We acknowledge</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that the Laws have power to bind the Conſcience of a Christian in themſelves, but not from themſelves.</hi> Neither do the Scriptures bind the Conſcience becauſe they are Scriptures, but becauſe they were from God. So alſo the Book of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Statutes bindeth our Conſciences in it ſelf, but not from it ſelf, but from the Authority of the King, who only in the right of God has the legiſlative Powers. Again he ſaith <hi>We acknowledge that in doubtful caſes, the Soveraign and the Law are always preſumed to be in the right.</hi> If he preſume they are in the right, how dare he preſume that the caſes they determine are doubtful? But ſaith he, <hi>in evident caſes which admit no doubt it is always better to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God than man.</hi> Yes, and in doubtful caſes alſo ſay I. But not always better to obey the inferior Paſtors than the Supream Paſtor, which is the King. But what are thoſe caſes that admit no doubt? I know but very few, and thoſe are ſuch as his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was not much acquainted with.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>But it is not worthy of my labour, nor any part of my intention, to purſue every ſhadow of a Queſtion which he ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:33138:63"/>It ſhall ſuffice to gather a Poſie of Flowers (or rather a bundle of Weeds) out of his Writings, and preſent them to the Reader, who will eaſily diſtinguiſh them from healthful Plants by the rankneſs of their ſmell. Such are theſe which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>As for the following Poſie of Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, there wants no more to make them ſweet, than to wipe off the Venome blown upon ſome of them by his Lordſhips breath.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>To be delighted in the imagination only of being poſſeſſed of another man's Goods, Servants, or Wife, without any intention to take them from him by force or fraud, is no breach of the Law which ſaith, Thou ſhalt not covet.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>What man was there ever whoſe imagination of any thing he thought would pleaſe him, whe not ſome delight? Or what ſin is there, where there is not ſo much as an intention to do injuſtice? But his Lordſhip would not diſtinguiſh between delight and purpoſe, nor between a Wiſh and a Will. This was venome. I believe, that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip himſelf even before he was Married took ſome delight in the thought of it, and yet the Woman then was not his own. All love is delight, but all love is not ſin. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this love of that which is not yet a mans
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:33138:64"/>own, the World had not been Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>If a Man by the terror of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent death be compelled to do a Fact againſt the Law, he is totally excuſed, becauſe no Law can oblige a Man to abandon his own preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, nature compelleth him to the Fact.</hi> The like Doctrine he hath elſewhere. <hi>When the Actor doth any thing against the Law of Nature by the Command of the Author, if he be obliged by former Covenants to obey him, not he, but the Author breaketh the Law of Nature.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſecond Flower is both ſweet and wholſom.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>It is a Doctrine repugnant to Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Society, that whatſoever a man does againſt his Conſcience is ſin.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis plain, that, to do what a man thinks in his own Conſcience to be ſin, is ſin; for it is a contempt of the Law it ſelf; and from thence ignorant men, our of an erroneous Conſcience, diſobey the Law which is pernicious to all Government.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>The Kingdom of God is not ſhut but to them that ſin, that is, to them who have not performed due obedience to the Laws of God; nor to them, if they believe the neceſſary Articles of the Christian Faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:33138:64"/>
                     <p n="5">5. <hi>We muſt know that the true acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſin is Repentance it ſelf.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6. <hi>An opinion publickly appointed to be taught cannot be Hereſie, nor the Soveraign Princes that Authoriſed the ſame Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>The 4th. 5th. and 6th. ſmoll well. But to ſay, that the Soveraign Prince in <hi>England</hi> is a Heretick, or that an Act of Parliament is Heretical, ſtinks abominably, as 'twas thought <hi>Primo Elizabethae.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="7">7. <hi>Temporal and Spiritual govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are but two words to make men ſee dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and mistake their lawful Soveraign,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>There is no other Government in this Life, neither, of State, nor Religion but Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">8. <hi>It is manifeſt, that they who permit a contrary Doctrine to that which themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and think neceſſary</hi> [to Salvation] <hi>do against their Conſciences, and Will, as much as in them lyeth the eternal destruction of their Subjects.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>The 7th. and 8th. are Roſes and Jaſſamin. But his leaving out the words <hi>[to Salvation]</hi> was venome.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="9">9. <hi>Subjects ſin if they do not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God according to the Laws of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:33138:65"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>The 9th. he hath poiſoned, and made it, not mine; he quotes my Book <hi>de Cive</hi> Cap. 15.19. Where I ſay, <hi>Regnante Deo per ſolam rationem naturalem,</hi> that is, <hi>Before the Scripture was given,</hi> they ſinned that refuſed to worſhip God, according to the Rites and Ceremonies of the Country, which hath no ill ſcent, but to undutiful Subjects.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="10">10. <hi>To believe in Jeſus</hi> [in Jeſum] <hi>is the ſame as to believe that Jeſus is Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo it is always in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="11">11. <hi>There can be no contradiction between the Laws of God, and the Laws of a Christian Common-wealth.</hi> Yet, we ſee Chriſtian Common-wealths daily contradict one another.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>The 11th. is alſo good. But his Lordſhip's inſtance, <hi>That Christian Common-wealths contradict one another,</hi> have nothing to do here. Their Laws do indeed contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict one another, but contradict not the Law of God. For God Commands their Subjects to obey them in all things, and his Lordſhip himſelf confeſſeth that their Laws, though erroneous, bind the Conſcience. But Chriſtian Common-wealths would ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome contradict one another, if they made no Doctrine Law, but ſuch as were neceſſary to Salvation.</p>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:33138:65"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="12">12. <hi>No man giveth but with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of ſome good to himſelf. Of all vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Acts, the Object is to every man his own good. Moſes,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the <hi>Decij.</hi> were not of his mind.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>That which his Lordſhip adds to the 12th. namely, that <hi>Moſes,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the <hi>Decij</hi> were not of my mind is falſe. For the two former did what they did for a good to themſelves, which was eternal Life; and the <hi>Decij</hi> for a good Fame after death. And his Lordſhip alſo, if he had believed there is an eternal happineſs to come, or thought a good Fame after death to be any thing worth, he would have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected all his actions towards them, and have deſpiſed the Wealth and Titles of the preſent World.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="13">13. <hi>There is no natural knowledge of man's estate after death, much leſs of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward which is then to be given to breach of Faith, but only a belief grounded upon other mens ſaying, that they know it ſupernaturally, or that they know thoſe that knew them that knew others that knew it ſupernaturally.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>The 13th. is good and freſh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="14">14. David's <hi>killing of</hi> Uriah <hi>was no injury to</hi> Uriah, <hi>becauſe the right to do what he pleaſed was given him by</hi> Uriah <hi>himſelf.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:33138:66"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>David himſelf makes this good, in ſaying, <hi>To thee only have I ſinned.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="15">15. <hi>To whom it belongeth to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine controverſies which may ariſe from the divers interpretations of Scripture, he hath an imperial power over all men which acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Scripture to be the Word of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="16">16. <hi>What is Theft, what is Murder, what is Adultery, and univerſally what is an inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is known by the Civil Law, that is, by the Commands of the Soveraign.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>For the 15th. he ſhould have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted it with the Head of the Church. And as to the 16th. I would have asked him by what other Law his Lordſhip would have it determined what is Theft, or what is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, than by the Laws' made in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or by the Laws which diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum?</hi> His Lordſhips ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance ſmells rankly ('tis his own phraſe) in this and many other places (which I have let paſs) of his own intereſt. The King tells us what is ſin, in that he tells us what is Law. He hath authoriſed the Clergy to dehort the people from ſin, and to exhort them, by good motives, (both from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and Reaſon) to obey the Laws; and ſuppoſeth them (though under forty years old) by the help they have in the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, able in caſe the Law be not written, to teach the people old and young, what
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:33138:66"/>they ought to follow in doubtful caſes of Conſcience, that is to ſay, they are autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed to expound the Laws of Nature; but not ſo as to make it a doubtful caſe whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the King's Laws be to be obeyed or not. All they ought to do is from the King's Authority. And therefore this my Doctrine is no Weed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="17">17. He admitteth inceſtuous <hi>Copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> of the Heathens, <hi>according to their Heatheniſh Laws to have been lawful Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages.</hi> Though the Scripture teach us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, that for thoſe abominations the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> ſpued our her Inhabitants, <hi>Levit.</hi> 18.28.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>The 17th. he hath corrupted with a falſe interpretation of the Text. For in that Chapter from the beginning to verſe 20, are forbidden Marriages in certain de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of kindred. From verſe 20, which begins with <hi>Moreover</hi> (to the 28th.) are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Sacrificing of Children to <hi>Molech,</hi> and Prophaning of God's name, and Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery with Man and Beaſt, with this cauſe expreſt <hi>(For all theſe abominations have the men of the Land done which were before you, and the Land is defiled) That the Land ſpue not you out alſo.</hi> As for Marriages within the degrees prohibited, they are not refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the abominations of the Heathen. Beſides, for ſome time after <hi>Adam,</hi> ſuch Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages were neceſſary.</p>
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:33138:67"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="18">18. <hi>I ſay that no other Article of Faith beſides this, that Jeſus is Christ, is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to a Chriſtian man for Salvation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="19">19. <hi>Becauſe Christ's Kingdom is not of this World, therefore neither can his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, unleſs they be Kings, require obedience in his name. They have no right of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, no power to make Laws.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe two ſmell comfortably, and of Scripture. The contrary Doctrine ſmells of Ambition and encroachment of Jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or Rump of the <hi>Roman</hi> Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p n="20">20. I paſs by his errors about Oaths about Vows, about the Reſurrection, about the Kingdom of Chriſt, about the Power of the Keys, Binding, Looſing, Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> his ignorant miſtakes of <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum congrui</hi> and <hi>condigni,</hi> active and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive obedience, and many more, for fear of being tedious to the Reader.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>The tears of School Divinity, of which numer are <hi>meritum congrui, meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum condigni,</hi> and <hi>paſſive obedience,</hi> are ſo obſcure as no man living can tell what they mean, ſo that they that uſe them may admit or deny their meaning, as it ſhall ſerve their turns. I ſaid not that this was their mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but that I thought it was ſo. For no man living can tell what a School man means by his words. Therefore I expounded them
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:33138:67"/>according to their true ſignification. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <hi>ex condigno</hi> is when a thing is deſerved by Pact; as when I ſay the Labourer is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of his hire, I mean <hi>meritum ex condig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no.</hi> But when a man of his own grace throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Money among the people, with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention that what part ſoever of it any of them could catch, he that catcheth merits it, not by Pact, nor by precedent Merit, as a Labourer, but becauſe it was congruent to the purpoſe of him that caſt it amongſt them. In all other meaning theſe words are but Jargon, which his Lordſhip had learnt by rote. Alſo <hi>paſſive obedience</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies nothing, except it may be called <hi>paſſive obedience</hi> when a man refraineth himſelf, from doing what the Law hath forbidden. For in his Lordſhip's ſenſe the Thief that is hang'd for ſtealing hath fulfilled the Law; which I think is abſurd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>J. D.</speaker>
                     <p>His whole works are a heap of miſhapen Errors, and abſurd Paradoxes, vent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the confidence of a Jugler, the brags of a Mountebank, and the Authority of ſome <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> or third <hi>Cato,</hi> lately dropped down from Heaven.</p>
                     <p>Thus we have ſeen how the <hi>Hobbian</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples do deſtroy the Exiſtence, the Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, the Ubiquity, the Eternity, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finiteneſs of God, the Doctrine of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinity, the Hypoſtatical Union, the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:33138:68"/>Kingly Sacerdotal and Prophetical Office of Chriſt, the Being and Operation of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, Heaven, Hell, Angels, Devils, the Immortality of the Soul, the Catholick and all National Churches; the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, holy Orders, the holy Sacraments, the whole frame of Religion, and the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God; the Laws of Nature, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality of Goodneſs, Juſtice, Piety, Honeſty, Conſcience, and all that is Sacred. If his Diſciples have ſuch an implicite Faith, that they can digeſt all theſe things, they may feed with <hi>Ostriches.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>T. H.</speaker>
                     <p>He here concludes his firſt Chapter with bitter Reproaches, to leave in his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (as he thought) a ſting, ſuppoſing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps that he will Read nothing but the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and end of his Book, as is the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of many men. But to make him loſe that petty piece of cunning, I muſt deſire of the Reader one of theſe two things. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he would read with it the places of my <hi>Leviathan</hi> which he cites, and ſee not only how he anſwers my arguments, but alſo what the arguments are which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth againſt them; or elſe that, he would forbear to condemn me, ſo much as in his thought; for otherwiſe he is unjuſt. The name of Biſhop is of great Authority, but theſe words are not the words of a Biſhop, but of a paſſionate School-man, too fierce
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:33138:68"/>and unſeemly in any man whatſoever. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, they are untrue. Who that knows me will ſay I have the confidence of a Jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, or that I uſe to brag of any thing, much leſs that I play the Mountebank? What my works are, he was no fit Judge. But now he has provoked me, I will ſay thus much of them, that neither he, if he had lived could, nor I if I would, can extinguiſh the light which is ſet up in the World by the greateſt part of them; and for theſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines which he impugneth, I have few op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers, but ſuch whoſe Profit, or whoſe Fame in Learning is concerned in them. He accuſes me firſt of deſtroying the Exiſtence of God, that is to ſay, he would make the World believe I were an Atheiſt. But up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what ground? Becauſe I ſay, that God is a Spirit, but <hi>Corporeal.</hi> But to ſay that, is allowed me by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that ſays <hi>There is a Spiritual Body, and there is an Animal Body.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. He that holds that there is a God, and that God is really ſomewhat (for <hi>Body</hi> is doubtleſly a <hi>real Subſtance</hi>) is as far from being an Atheiſt, as is poſſible to be. But he that ſays God is an <hi>Incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Subſtance,</hi> no man can be ſure whether he be an Atheiſt or not. For no man living can tell whether there be any <hi>Subſtance</hi> at all, that is not alſo <hi>Corporeal.</hi> For neither
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:33138:69"/>the word <hi>Incorporeal,</hi> nor <hi>Immaterial,</hi> nor any word equivalent to it is to be found in Scripture, or in Reaſon. But on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary that <hi>the Godhead dwelleth bodily in Christ,</hi> is found in <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.9. and <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> maintains that God is either a <hi>Corporeal Substance</hi> or <hi>Nothing.</hi> Nor was he ever condemned for it by the Church. For why? Not only <hi>Tertullian</hi> but all the learned call <hi>Body,</hi> not only that which one can ſee, but alſo whatſoever has magnitude, or that is ſomewhere; for they had greater reverence for the Divine Subſtance than that they durſt think it had no <hi>Magnitude</hi> or was <hi>no where.</hi> But they that hold God to be a Phantaſm, as did the Exorciſts in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that is, ſuch a thing as were at that time thought to be the Sprights that were ſaid to walk in Church-yards, and to be the Souls of men buried, they do abſolutely make God to be nothing at all. But how? Were they Atheiſts? No. For though by ignorance of the conſequence they ſaid that which was equivolent to Atheiſm, yet in their hearts they thought God a Subſtance, and would alſo, if they had known what <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance</hi> and what <hi>Corporeal</hi> meant, have ſaid he was a Corporeal Subſtance. So that this <hi>Atheiſm by conſequence</hi> is a very eaſie thing to be fallen into, even by the moſt Godly men
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:33138:69"/>of the Church. He alſo that ſays that God is <hi>wholly here,</hi> and <hi>wholly there,</hi> and <hi>wholly every where,</hi> deſtroys by conſequence the Unity of God, and the Infiniteneſs of God, and the Simplicity of God. And this the Schoolmen do, and are therefore <hi>Atheists by conſequence,</hi> and yet they do not all ſay in their hearts that there is no God. So al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his Lordſhip by exempting the Will of man from being ſubject to the neceſſity of God's Will or Decree, denies by <hi>conſequence</hi> the Divine Praeſcience, which alſo will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to <hi>Atheiſm by conſequence.</hi> But out of this that God is a <hi>Spirit corporeal</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely pure,</hi> there can no unworthy or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonourable conſequence be drawn. Thus far to his Lordſhip's firſt Chapter in Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of my <hi>Leviathan,</hi> as to matter of Religion; and eſpecially to wipe off that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt ſlander caſt upon me by the Biſhop of <hi>Derry.</hi> As for the ſecond Chapter which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns my Civil Doctrines, ſince my errors there, if there be any, will not tend very much to my diſgrace, I will not take the pains to anſwer it.</p>
                     <p>Whereas his Lordſhip has talked in his diſcourſe here and there ignorantly of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and ſome others have not doubted to ſay publickly, that there be many Hereſies in my
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:33138:70"/>
                        <hi>Leviathan;</hi> I will add hereunto for a general anſwer an Hiſtorical relation concerning the word Hereſie from the firſt uſe of it amongſt the <hi>Graecians,</hi> till this preſent time.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33138:70"/>
                  <p>AN Hiſtorical Narration CONCERNING HERESIE, AND THE Puniſhment thereof.</p>
                  <p>BY <hi>THOMAS HOBBES</hi> OF <hi>MALMESBURY.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>At veluti Pueri trepidant, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> omnia caecis</l>
                     <l>In tenebris metuunt: Sic nos in luce timemus</l>
                     <l>Interdum nihilo quae ſunt metuenda magis, quàm</l>
                     <l>Quae Pueri in tenebris pavitant, metuunt<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> futura.</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Lucr.</hi> lib. <hi>2.3, 6.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1682.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="license">
                  <pb facs="tcp:33138:71"/>
                  <p>Haereſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Larvas, Seclarum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mania Monſtra</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hobbius</hi> invicto diſpulit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genio.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:33138:71"/>
                  <head>AN Hiſtorical Narration CONCERNING HERESIE, AND THE Puniſhment thereof.</head>
                  <p>THE word <hi>Hereſie</hi> is Greek, and ſignifies a taking of any thing, and particularly the taking of an Opinion. After the ſtudy of Philoſophy begun in <hi>Greece,</hi> and the Philoſophers diſagreeing amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, had ſtarted many Queſtions, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly about things Natural, but alſo Moral and Civil; becauſe every man took what Opinion he pleaſed, each ſeveral Opinion was called a <hi>Hereſie;</hi> which ſignified no more than a private Opinion, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to truth or falſhood. The begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:33138:72"/>of theſe Hereſies were chiefly <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, Plato, Aristotle, Epicurus, Zeno;</hi> men who as they held many Errors, ſo alſo found they out many true and uſeful Doctrines, in all kinds of Learning: and for that cauſe were well eſteemed of by the greateſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages of their own times; and ſo alſo were ſome few of their Followers.</p>
                  <p>But the reſt, ignorant men, and very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten needy Knaves, having learned by heart the Opinions of theſe admir'd Philoſophers, and pretending to take after them, made uſe thereof to get their Living by the teaching of Rich mens Children that happened to be in love with thoſe great Names. Tho' by their impertinent Diſcourſe, ſordid and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Manners, they were generally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, of what Sect or Hereſie ſoever; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were <hi>Pythagoreans,</hi> or <hi>Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micks</hi> (Followers of <hi>Plato</hi>) or <hi>Peripate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> (Followers of <hi>Aristotle: Epicureans</hi> or <hi>Stoicks</hi>) (Followers of <hi>Zeno</hi>) For theſe were the names of Hereſies, or (as the <hi>Latines</hi> call them) <hi>Sects, à ſequendo,</hi> ſo much talkt of from after the time of <hi>Alexander</hi> till this preſent day, and that have perpetually troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or deceived the people with whom they lived, and were never more numerous than in the time of the Primitive Church.</p>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:33138:72"/>
                  <p>The Hereſie of <hi>Aristotle,</hi> by the Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of time has had the good fortune to be predominant over the reſt. However originally the name of <hi>Hereſie</hi> was no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, nor the word <hi>Heretick</hi> at all in uſe. Tho' the ſeveral Sects, eſpecially the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cureans</hi> and the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> hated one another; and the <hi>Stoicks</hi> being the fiercer men, uſed to revile thoſe that differed from them with the moſt deſpightful words they could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</p>
                  <p>It cannot be doubted, but that, by the preaching of the Apoſtles and Diſciples of Chriſt in <hi>Greece</hi> and other parts of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire, full of theſe Philoſophers, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of men were converted to the Chriſtian Faith, ſome really, and ſome feign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, for factious ends, or for need; (for Chriſtians lived then in common, and were charitable:) and becauſe moſt of theſe Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers had better skill in Diſputing and Oratory than the Common people, and thereby were better qualified both to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and propagate the Goſpel, there is no doubt (I ſay) but moſt of the Paſtors of the Primitive Church were for that reaſon choſen out of the number of theſe Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers; who retaining ſtill many Doctrines which they had taken up on the authority of their former Maſters, whom they had in reverence, endeavoured many of them to
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:33138:73"/>draw the Scriptures every one to his own Hereſie. And thus at firſt entred Hereſie into the Church of Chriſt. Yet theſe men were all of them Chriſtians; as they were when they were firſt baptized: Nor did they deny the Authority of thoſe Writings which were left them by the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts, tho' they interpreted them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times with a bias to their former Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy. And this Diſſention amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, was a great ſcandal to the Unbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and which not only obſtructed the way of the Goſpel, but alſo drew ſcorn and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Perſecution upon the Church.</p>
                  <p>For remedy whereof, the chief Paſtors of Churches did uſe, at the riſing of any new Opinion, to aſſemble themſelves for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amining and determining of the ſame; wherein, if the Author of the Opinion were convinced of his Error, and ſubſcribed to the Sentence of the Church aſſembled, then all was well again: but if he ſtill perſiſted in it, they laid him aſide, and conſidered him but as an Heathen man; which to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Chriſtian, was a great Ignominy, and of force to make him conſider better of his own Doctrine; and ſometimes brought him to the acknowledgment of the Truth. But other puniſhment they could inflict none, that being a right appropriated to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Power. So that all the puniſhment the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:33138:73"/>Church could inflict, was only Ignominy; and that among the Faithful, conſiſting in this, that his company was by all the Godly avoided, and he himſelf branded with the name of <hi>Heretick</hi> in oppoſition to the whole Church, that condemned his Doctrine. So that <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Heretick</hi> were terms re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative; and here it was that Heretick be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came to be a Name, and a name of Diſgrace, both together.</p>
                  <p>The firſt and moſt troubleſome Hereſies in the Primitive Church, were about the Trinity. For (according to the uſual cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity of Natural Philoſophers) they could not abſtain from diſputing the very firſt Principles of Chriſtianity, into which they were baptized, <hi>In the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Some there were that made them allegorical. Others would make one Creator of Good, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of Evil; which was in effect to ſet up two Gods, one contrary to another; ſuppoſing that cauſation of evil could not be attributed to God, without Impiety. From which Doctrine they are not far di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, that now make the firſt cauſe of ſinful actions to be every man as to his own ſin. Others there were that would have God to be a body with Parts organical, as Face, Hands, Fore-parts and Back-parts. Others, that Chriſt had no real body, but was a
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:33138:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>meer Phantaſm: (For Phantaſms were taken then, and have been ever ſince, by unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſuperſtitious men, for things real and ſubſiſtent.) Others denyed the Divinity of Chriſt. Others, that Chriſt being God and Man, was two Perſons. Others confeſt he was one Perſon, and withal that he had but one Nature. And a great many other He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies aroſe from the too much adherence to the Philoſophy of thoſe times, whereof ſome were ſuppreſt for a time by St. <hi>John</hi>'s pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing his Goſpel, and ſome by their own unreaſonableneſs vaniſhed, and ſome laſted till the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, and after.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Constantine</hi> the Great (made ſo by the aſſiſtance and valour of the Chriſtian Souldiers) had attained to be the only <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperor, he alſo himſelf became a Chriſtian, and cauſed the Temples of the Heathen Gods to be demoliſhed, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized Chriſtian Religion only to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. But towards the latter end of his time, there aroſe a Diſpute in the City of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> between <hi>Alexander</hi> the Biſhop, and <hi>Arius</hi> a Presbyter of the ſame City; wherein <hi>Arius</hi> maintained, firſt, That Chriſt was inferiour to his Father; and afterwards, That he was no God, alleadging the words of Chriſt, <hi>My Father is greater than I.</hi> The Biſhop on the contrary alleadging the words
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:33138:74"/>of St. <hi>John, And the Word was God;</hi> and the words of St. <hi>Thomas, My Lord and my God.</hi> This Controverſie preſently amongſt the Inhabitants and Souldiers of <hi>Alexandria</hi> became a Quarrel, and was the cauſe of much Bloodſhed in and about the City; and was likely then to ſpread further, as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it did. This ſo far concerned the Emperors Civil Government, that he thought it neceſſary to call a General Council of all the Biſhops and other eminent Divines throughout the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, to meet at the City of <hi>Nice.</hi> When they were aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, they preſented the Emperor with Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels of Accuſation one againſt another. When he had received theſe Libels into his hands, he made an Oration to the Fathers aſſembled, exhorting them to agree, and to fall in hand with the ſettlement of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith, for which cauſe he had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled them, ſaying, Whatſoever they ſhould decree therein, he would cauſe to be obſerved. <hi>This may perhaps ſeem a greater indifferency than would in theſe dayes be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of.</hi> But ſo it is in the Hiſtory; and the Articles of Faith neceſſary to Salvation, were not thought then to be ſo many as afterwards they were defined to be by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:33138:75"/>
                  <p>When <hi>Constantine</hi> had ended his Oration, he cauſed the aforeſaid Libels to be caſt into the fire, as became a wiſe King and a chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Chriſtian. This done, the Fathers fell in hand with their buſineſs, and following the method of a former Creed, now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>The Apoſtles Creed,</hi> made a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, <hi>viz. I believe in one God, the Father Almighty, maker of Heaven and Earth, and of all things viſible and inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> (in which is condemned the Poly theiſm of the Gentiles.) <hi>And in one Lord Jeſus Chriſt the only begotten Son of God,</hi> (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the many ſons of the many Gods of the Heathen.) <hi>Begotten of his Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all worlds, God of God,</hi> (againſt the <hi>Arians</hi>) <hi>Very God of very God,</hi> (againſt the <hi>Valentinians,</hi> and againſt the Hereſie of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles,</hi> and others, who made Chriſt a meer Phantaſm.) <hi>Light of Light,</hi> [This was put in for explication, and uſed before to that purpoſe, by <hi>Tertullian.</hi>] <hi>Begotten, not made, being of one Subſtance with the Father.</hi> In this again they condemn the Doctrine of <hi>Arius:</hi> for this word <hi>Of one ſubstance,</hi> in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time <hi>Conſubstantialis,</hi> but in Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is, <hi>Of one Eſſence,</hi> was put as a Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to diſcern an <hi>Arian</hi> from a <hi>Catholick:</hi> And much ado there was about it. <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> himſelf, at the paſſing of this Creed, took notice of it for a hard word; but yet
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:33138:75"/>approved of it, ſaying. That in a divine Myſtery it was fit to uſe <hi>divina &amp; arcana Verba;</hi> that is, divine words, and hidden from humane underſtanding; calling that word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, divine, not becauſe it was in the divine Scripture, (for it is not there) but becauſe it was to him <hi>Arcanum,</hi> that is, not ſufficiently underſtood. <hi>And in this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain appeared the indifferency of the Emperor, and that he had for his end, in the calling of the Synod, not ſo much the Truth, as the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of the Doctrine, and peace of his People that depended on it.</hi> The cauſe of the obſcurity of this word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, proceeded chiefly from the difference between the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Dialect, in the Philoſophy of the <hi>Peripateticks.</hi> The firſt Principle of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all Nations, is, <hi>That God is,</hi> that is to ſay, that God really is Something, and not a meer fancy; but that which is really ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, is conſiderable alone by it ſelf, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſomewhere.</hi> In which ſence a man is a thing real: for I can conſider him <hi>to be,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſidering any other thing <hi>to be</hi> beſides him. And for the ſame reaſon, the Earth, the Air, the Stars, Heaven, and their Parts, are all of them things real. And becauſe whatſoever is real here, or there, or in any place, has Dimenſions, that is to ſay, Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude; and that which hath Magnitude, whether it be viſible or inviſible, finite or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:33138:76"/>is called by all the Learned <hi>a Body.</hi> It followeth, that all real things, in that they are <hi>ſomewhere,</hi> are Corporeal. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, Eſſence, Deity, Humanity, and ſuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like names, ſignifie nothing that can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, without firſt conſidering there is an <hi>Ens,</hi> a God, a Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So alſo if there be any real thing that is <hi>white</hi> or <hi>black, hot</hi> or <hi>cold,</hi> the ſame may be conſidered by it ſelf; but whiteneſs, blackneſs, heat, coldneſs, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be conſidered, unleſs it be firſt ſuppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that there is ſome real thing to which they are attributed. Theſe real things are called by the Latine Philoſophers, <hi>Entia ſubjecta, ſubstantiae;</hi> and by the Greek Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which are Incorporeal, are called by the Greek Philoſophers, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; but moſt of the Latine Philoſophers uſe to convert <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>into <hi>ſubſtantia,</hi> and ſo confound real and corporeal things with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporeal; which is not well: For Eſſence and Subſtance ſignifie divers things. And this miſtake is received, and continues ſtill in theſe parts, in all Diſputes both of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, and Divinity: For in truth <hi>Eſſentia</hi> ſignifies no more, than if we ſhould talk ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculouſly of the <hi>Iſneſs</hi> of the thing that is. <hi>[By whom all things were made.]</hi> This is proved out of St. <hi>John, cap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1, 2, 3. and <hi>Heb. cap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. and that again out
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:33138:76"/>of <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. where God is ſaid to create eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing by his ſole Word, as when he ſaid, <hi>Let there be Light, and there was Light.</hi> And then, that Chriſt was that Word; and in the beginning with God, may be gathered out of divers places of <hi>Moſes, David,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Prophets. Nor was it ever queſtioned amongſt Chriſtians (except by the <hi>Arians</hi>) but that Chriſt was God Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and his Incarnation eternally decreed. But the Fathers, all that write Expoſitions on this Creed, could not forbear to philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophize upon it, and moſt of them out of the Principles of <hi>Aristotle:</hi> Which are the ſame the School-men now uſe; as may part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear by this, that many of them, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their. Treatiſes of Religion, have affected to publiſh Logick and Phyſick Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples according to the ſenſe of <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> as <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and <hi>Damaſcene.</hi> And ſo ſome later Divines of <hi>Note,</hi> ſtill confound the Concreet with the Abſtract, <hi>Deus</hi> with <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, Ens</hi> with <hi>Eſſentia, Sapiens</hi> with <hi>Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Aeternus</hi> with <hi>Aeternitas.</hi> If it be for exact and rigid Truth ſake, why do they not ſay alſo, that Holineſs is a Holy man, Covetouſneſs a Covetous man, Hypocriſie an Hypocrite, and Drunkenneſs a Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, and the like, but that it is an Error? The Fathers agree that the Wiſdom of God is the eternal Son of God, by whom all
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:33138:77"/>things were made, and that he was incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate by the Holy Ghoſt, if they meant it in the Abſtract: For if <hi>Deitas</hi> abſtracted be <hi>Deus,</hi> we make two Gods of one. This was well underſtood by <hi>Damaſcene,</hi> in his Treatiſe <hi>De Fide Orthodoxa,</hi> (which is an Expoſition of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed) where he denies abſolutely that <hi>Deitas</hi> is <hi>Deus,</hi> leſt (ſeeing God was made man) it ſhould fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, the Deity was made man; which is contrary to the Doctrine of all the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers. The Attributes therefore of God in the Abſtract, when they are put for God, are put <hi>Metonymically;</hi> which is a common thing in Scripture; for Example, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.28. where it is ſaid, <hi>Before the mountains were ſetled, before the Hills was I brought forth;</hi> the Wiſdom there ſpoken of being the Wiſdom of God, ſignifies the ſame with the wiſe God. This kind of ſpeaking is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ordinary in all Languages. This conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, ſuch abſtracted words ought not to be uſed in Arguing, and eſpecially in the deducing the Articles of our Faith; though in the Language of God's eternal Worſhip, and in all Godly Diſcourſes, they cannot be avoided: And the Creed it ſelf is leſs diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to be aſſented to in its own words, than in all ſuch Expoſitions of the Fathers. <hi>Who for us men and our Salvation came down from Heaven, and was uncarnate by the
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:33138:77"/>holy Ghoſt of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and was made Man.</hi> I have not read of any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception to this: For where <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his Creed ſays of the Son, <hi>He was not made, but begotten,</hi> it is to be underſtood of the Son as he was God Eternal; whereas here it is ſpoken of the Son as he is man. And of the Son alſo as he was man, it may be ſaid he was begotten of the Holy Ghoſt; for a Woman conceiveth not but of him that begetteth; which is alſo confirmed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1, 20. <hi>That which is begotten in her</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>is of the Holy Ghoſt. And was alſo Crucified for us under</hi> Pontius Pilate: <hi>he ſuffered and was buried: And the third day he roſe again according to the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and aſcended into Heaven: and fitteth on the right hand of the Father; And he ſhall come again with Glory to judge both the Quick and the Dead. Whoſe Kingdom ſhall have no end.</hi> [Of this part of the Creed I have not met with any doubt made by any Chriſtian.] Hither the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice</hi> proceedeth in their general Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, and no further.</p>
                  <p>This finiſhed, ſome of the Biſhops pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the Council (ſeventeen or eighteen, whereof <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> was one) not ſufficiently ſatisfied, refuſed to ſubſcribe till this Doctrine of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>ſhould be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter explained. Thereupon the Council De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:33138:78"/>that whoſoever ſhall ſay that God hath parts, ſhall be Anathematized; to which the ſaid Biſhops ſubſcribed. And <hi>Euſebius</hi> by Order of the Council wrote a Letter, the Copies whereof were ſent to every abſent Biſhop, that being ſatisfied with the reaſon of their ſubſcribing, they alſo ſhould ſubſcribe. The reaſon they gave of their Subſcription was this, <hi>That they had now a form of words preſcribed, by which, as a Rule, they might guide themſelves ſo, as not to violate the Peace of the Church.</hi> By this it is manifeſt, that no man was an Heretick, but he that in plain and direct words contradicted that Form by the Church preſcribed, and that no man could be made <hi>an Heretick by Conſequence.</hi> And becauſe the ſaid Form was not put into the body of the Creed, but directed only to the Biſhops, there was no reaſon to puniſh any Lay-per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that ſhould ſpeak to the contrary.</p>
                  <p>But what was the meaning of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>That God has no Parts?</hi> Was it made Hereſie to ſay, that God, who is a real ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, cannot be conſidered or ſpoken of as <hi>here</hi> or <hi>there,</hi> or any where, which are parts of places? Or that there is any real thing without length every way, that is to ſay, which hath no Magnitude at all, finite nor infinite? Or is there any whole ſubſtance, whoſe two halves or three thirds are not
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:33138:78"/>the ſame with that whole? Or did they mean to condemn the Argument of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> by which he confuted <hi>Apelles</hi> and other Hereticks of his time; namely, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever was not Corporeal, was nothing but Fantaſm, and not Corporeal,</hi> for Heretical? No certainly, no Divines ſay that. They went to eſtabliſh the Doctrine of <hi>One indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidual God in Trinity;</hi> to aboliſh the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of ſpecies in God, not the diſtinction of <hi>here</hi> and <hi>there</hi> in ſubſtance. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> asked the <hi>Corinthians, Is Chriſt divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</hi> He did not think they thought him impoſſible to be conſidered as having hands and feet, but that they might think him (according to the manner of the Gentiles) one of the Sons of God, as <hi>Arius</hi> did; but not the only begotten Son of God. And thus alſo it is expounded in the Creed of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> who was preſent in that Council, by theſe words, <hi>Not confounding the Perſons, nor dividing the Substances;</hi> that is to ſay, that God is not divided into three Perſons, as man is divided into <hi>Peter, James,</hi> and <hi>John;</hi> nor are the three perſons one and the ſame perſon. But <hi>Aristotle,</hi> and from him all the <hi>Greek</hi> Fathers, and other Learned Men, when they diſtinguiſh the general La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of a word, they call it Diviſion; as when they divide. <hi>Animal</hi> into Man and Beaſt, they call theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Species;</hi> and when
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:33138:79"/>they again divide the <hi>Species</hi> Man into <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> they call theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>partes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuae.</hi> And by this confounding the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of the ſubſtance with the diſtinction of words, divers men have been led into the Error of attributing to God a Name, which is not the name of any ſubſtance at all, <hi>viz. Incorporeal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By theſe words, <hi>God has no parts,</hi> thus explained, together with the part of the <hi>Creed</hi> which was at that time agreed on, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe Hereſies which were antecedent to that firſt General Council, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; as that of <hi>Manes,</hi> who appeared about thirty years before the Reign of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine,</hi> by the firſt Article, <hi>I believe in one God;</hi> though in other words it ſeems to me to remain ſtill in the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which ſo aſcribeth a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Will to Men, as that their Will and Purpoſe to commit ſin, ſhould not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the Cauſe of all things, God; but originally from themſelves, or from the Devil. It may ſeem perhaps to ſome, that by the ſame words the <hi>Anthropomorphites</hi> alſo were then Condemned: And certainly, if by Parts were meant not perſons Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual, but Pieces, they were Condemned: For Face, Arms, Feet, and the like, are pieces. But this cannot be, for the <hi>Anthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pomorphites</hi> appeared not till the time of <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens</hi>
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:33138:79"/>the Emperor, which was after the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Nice</hi> between forty and fifty years; and was not condemned till the ſecond Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now for the Puniſhment of Hereticks ordained by <hi>Constantine,</hi> we read of none; but that Eccleſiaſtical Officers, Biſhops and other Preachers, if they refuſed to ſubſcribe to this Faith, or taught the contrary Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, were for the firſt Fault Deprived of their Offices, and for the ſecond Baniſhed. And thus did Hereſie, which at firſt was the name of private Opinion, and no Crime, by vertue of a Law of the Emperor, made only for the Peace of the Church, become a Crime in a Paſtor, and puniſhable with Deprivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on firſt, and next with Baniſhment.</p>
                  <p>After this part of the Creed was thus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, there aroſe preſently many new Hereſies, partly about the Interpretation of it, and partly about the Holy Ghoſt, of which the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council had not determined. Concerning the part eſtabliſhed, there aroſe Diſputes about the Nature of Chriſt, and the word <hi>Hypostaſis, id est,</hi> Subſtance; for of Perſons there was yet no mention made, the Creed being written in <hi>Greek,</hi> in which Language there is no, word that anſwereth to the <hi>Latine</hi> word <hi>Perſona.</hi> And the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, as the Fathers called it, of the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane and Divine Nature in Chriſt, <hi>Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical,</hi>
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:33138:80"/>cauſed <hi>Eutyches,</hi> and after him <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcorus,</hi> to affirm, there was but one Nature in Chriſt; thinking that whenſoever two things are united, they are one: And this was condemned as <hi>Arianiſm</hi> in the Councils of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> and <hi>Epheſus.</hi> Others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they thought two living and rational Subſtances, ſuch as are God and Man, muſt needs be alſo two <hi>Hypoſtaſes,</hi> maintained that Chriſt had two <hi>Hypostaſes:</hi> But theſe were two Hereſies condemned together. Then concerning the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Neſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, denied the Divinity thereof. And whereas about ſeventy years before the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> Council, there had been holden a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Council at <hi>Carthage,</hi> wherein it was Decreed, that thoſe Chriſtians which in the Perſecutions had denyed the Faith of Chriſt, ſhould not be received again into the Church unleſs they were again baptized: This alſo was condemned, though the Preſident in that Council were that moſt ſincere and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Chriſtian, <hi>Cyprian.</hi> And at laſt the Creed was made up entire as we have it, in the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonian</hi> Council, by addition of theſe words, <hi>And I believe in the Holy Ghoſt, the Lord and Giver of Life, who proceedeth from the Father and the Son. Who with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; the Son together is Worſhipped and Glorified. Who ſpake by the Prophets.
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:33138:80"/>And I believe one Catholick &amp; Apoſtolick Church. I acknowledge one Baptiſm for the Remiſſion of Sins. And I look for the Reſurrection of the Dead, and the Life of the World to come.</hi> In this addition are condemned, firſt the <hi>Neſtorians</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in theſe words, <hi>Who with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son together is worſhipped and glorified:</hi> And ſecondly the Doctrine of the Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>I believe one Baptiſm for the Remiſſion of Sins:</hi> For one Baptiſm is not there put as oppoſite to ſeveral ſorts or manners of Baptiſm, but to the iteration of it: St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> was a better Chriſtian than to allow any Baptiſm that was not in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. In the General Confeſſion of Faith contained in the Creed called the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, there is no mention of <hi>Hypostaſis,</hi> nor of Hypoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Union, nor of Corporeal, nor of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporeal, nor of Parts; the underſtanding of which words being not required of the Vulgar, but only of the Paſtors, whoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreement elſe might trouble the Church; nor were ſuch Points neceſſary to Salvation, but ſet abroach for oſtentation of Learning, or elſe to dazle men, with deſign to lead them towards ſome ends of their own. The Changes of prevalence in the Empire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Catholicks</hi> and the <hi>Arians,</hi> and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:33138:81"/>how the great <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> the moſt fierce of the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> was baniſhed by <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and afterwards reſtored, and again baniſhed, I let paſs; only it is to be remembred, that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> is ſuppos'd to have made his Creed then, when (baniſhed) he was in <hi>Rome, Liberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> being Pope; by whom, as is moſt likely, the word <hi>Hypoſtaſis,</hi> as it was in <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s Creed, was diſliked: For the <hi>Roman</hi> Church could never be brought to receive it but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead thereof uſed their own word <hi>Perſona.</hi> But the firſt and laſt words of that Creed the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> refuſed not: For they make every Article, not only thoſe of the body of the Creed, but all the Definitions of the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> Fathers to be ſuch, as a man cannot be ſaved, unleſs he believe them all ſtedfaſtly; though made only for Peace ſake, and to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite the minds of the Clergy, whoſe Diſputes were like to trouble the Peace of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. After theſe four firſt General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, the Power of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church grew up a pace; and either by the negligence or weakneſs of the ſucceeding Emperors, the Pope did what he pleaſed in Religion. <hi>There was no Doctrine which tended to the Power Eccleſiastical, or to the Reverence of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, the contradiction whereof was not by one Council or another made Hereſie, and puniſhed arbitrarily by the Emperors with Baniſhment or Death.</hi> And at laſt Kings themſelves, and
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:33138:81"/>Commonwealths, unleſs they purged their Dominions of Hereticks, were Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, Interdicted, and their Subjects let looſe upon them by the Pope; inſomuch as to an ingenuous and ſerious Chriſtian, there was nothing ſo dangerous as to enquire con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his own Salvation, of the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; the careleſs cold Chriſtian was ſafe, and the skilful Hypocrite a Saint. But this is a Story ſo well known, as I need not inſiſt upon it any longer, but proceed to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks here in <hi>England,</hi> and what Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were ordained for them by Acts of Parliament. All this while the Penal Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Hereticks were ſuch, as the ſeveral Princes and States, in their own Dominions, thought fit to enact. The Edicts of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors made their Puniſhments Capital, but for the manner of the Execution, left it to the Prefects of Provinces: And when other Kings and States intended (according to the Laws of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church) to extirpate Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, they ordained ſuch Puniſhment as they pleaſed. The firſt Law that was here made for the puniſhments of Hereticks called <hi>Lol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lards,</hi> and mentioned in the Statutes, was in the fifth year of the Reign of <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, occaſioned by the Doctrine of <hi>John Wickliff</hi> and his Followers; which <hi>Wickliff,</hi> becauſe no Law was yet ordained for his puniſhment in Parliament, by the favour of
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:33138:82"/>
                     <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt,</hi> the King's Son, during the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the third, had eſcaped. But in the fifth year of the next King, which was <hi>Richard</hi> the Second, there paſſed an Act of Parliament to this effect; That Sheriffs and ſome others ſhould have Commiſſions to apprehend ſuch as were certified by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to be Preachers of Hereſie, their Fautors, Maintainers and Abettors, and to hold them in ſtrong Priſon, till they ſhould juſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, according to the Law of Holy Church. So that hitherto there was no Law in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by which a Heretick could be put to Death, or otherways puniſhed, than by impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning him till he was reconciled to the Church. After this, in the next King's Reign, which was <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, Son of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Gaunt</hi> by whom <hi>Wickliffe</hi> had been favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>and who in his aſpiring to the Crown had needed the good Will of the Biſhops,</hi> was made a Law, in the ſecond Year of his Reign, wherein it was Enacted, That every Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary may convene before him, and impriſon any perſon ſuſpected of Hereſie; and that an obſtinate Heretick ſhall be burnt before the People.</p>
                  <p>In the next King's Reign, which was <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Fifth, in his Second year, was made an Act of Parliament, wherein it is declared, that the intent of Hereticks, called <hi>Lollards,</hi> was to ſubvert the Chriſtian Faith, the Law of God, the Church and the Realm: And that
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:33138:82"/>an Heretick convict ſhould forfeit all his Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimple Lands, Goods and Chattels, beſides the Puniſhment of Burning. Again, in the Five and Twentieth year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, it was Enacted, That an Heretick convict ſhall abjure his Hereſies, and refuſing ſo to do, or relapſing, ſhall be burnt in open place, for example of others. This Act was made after the putting down of the Pope's Authority: And by this it appears, that King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth intended no farther alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in Religion, than the recovering of his own Right Eccleſiaſtical. But in the firſt year of his Son King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth was made an Act, by which were repealed not only this Act, but alſo all former Acts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Doctrines, or matters of Religion; So that at this time there was no Law at all for the puniſhment of Hereticks.</p>
                  <p>Again, in the Parliament of the firſt and ſecond year of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> this Act of 1 <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. was not repealed, but made uſeleſs, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving the Statute of 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and freely put it in execution; inſomuch as it was De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, Whether or no they ſhould proceed upon that Statute againſt the Lady <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> the Queens Siſter.</p>
                  <p>The Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> not long after by the Death of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> coming to the Crown in the fifth year of her Reign, by Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament repealed in the firſt place all the Laws Eccleſiaſtical of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> with all other
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:33138:83"/>former Laws concerning the puniſhments of Hereticks, nor did ſhe enact any other puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in their place. In the ſecond place it was Enacted, That the Queen by her Letters Patents ſhould give a Commiſſion to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, with certain other perſons, in her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Name, to execute the Power Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical; in which Commiſſion the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners were forbidden to adjudge any thing to be Hereſie, which was not declared to be Hereſie by ſome of the firſt four General Councels: But there was no mention made of General Councels, but only in that branch of the Act which Authoriſed that Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, commonly called <hi>The High Commiſſion;</hi> nor was there in that Commiſſion any thing concerning how Hereticks were to be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, but it was granted to them, that they might declare or not declare, as they pleaſed, to be Hereſie or not Hereſie, any of thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines which had been Condemned for He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie in the firſt four General Councels. So that during the time that the ſaid High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion was in being, there was no Statute by which a Heretick could be puniſhed other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, than by the ordinary Cenſures of the Church; nor Doctrine accounted Hereſie, unleſs the Commiſſioners had actually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and publiſhed, That all that which was made Hereſie by thoſe Four Councels, ſhould be Hereſie alſo now: But I never heard that any ſuch Declaration was made either by
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:33138:83"/>Proclamation, or by Recording it in Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or by publick Printing, as in penal Laws is neceſſary; the breaches of it are excuſed by ignorance: Beſides, if Hereſie had been made Capital, or otherwiſe civilly puniſhable, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Four General Councels themſelves, or at leaſt the Points condemned in them, ought to have been Printed or put into Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Churches in Engliſh, becauſe without it, no man could know how to beware of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending againſt them.</p>
                  <p>Some men may perhaps ask, whether no body were Condemned and Burnt for Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, during the time of the High Commiſſion.</p>
                  <p>I have heard there were: But they which approve ſuch executions, may peradventure know better grounds for them than I do; but thoſe grounds are very well worthy to be enquired after.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, in the ſeventeenth year of the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, ſhortly after that the <hi>Scots</hi> had Rebelliouſly put down the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Government in <hi>Scotland,</hi> the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians of <hi>England</hi> endeavoured the ſame here. The King, though he ſaw the Rebels ready to take the Field, would not conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to that; but yet in hope to appeaſe them, was content to paſs an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the aboliſhing the High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. But though the High Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion were taken away, yet the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment having other ends beſides the ſetting
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:33138:84"/>up of the Presbyterate, purſued the Rebellion, and put down both Epiſcopacy and Monarchy, erecting a power by them called <hi>The Common-wealth,</hi> by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the <hi>Rump,</hi> which men obeyed not out of Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but for fear, nor was there any humane Laws left in force to reſtrain any man from Preaching or Writing any Doctrine concerning Religion that he pleaſed; and in this heat of the War, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to diſturb the Peace of the State, which then was none.</p>
                  <p>And in this time it was, that a Book called <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>athan,</hi> was written in defence of the King's Power, Temporal and Spiritual, without any word againſt Epiſcopacy, or againſt any Biſhop, or againſt the publick Doctrine of the Church. It pleas'd God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Twelve years after the Uſurpation of this <hi>Rump,</hi> to reſtore His moſt Gracious Majeſty that now is, to his Fathers Throne, and preſently His Majeſty reſtored the Biſhops, and pardoned the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians; but then both the one and the other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed in Parliament this Book of Hereſie, when nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Biſhops before the War had declared what was Hereſie, when if they had, it had been made void by the putting down of the High Commiſſion at the importunity of the Presbyterians: So fierce are men, for the moſt part, in diſpute, where either their Learning or Power is debated, that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think of the Laws, but as ſoon as they are offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they cry out, <hi>Crucifige;</hi> forgetting what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, even in caſe of obſtinate holding of an Error, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 24, 25. The Servant of the Lord muſt not ſtrive, but be gentle unto all men, apt to teach, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, in meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe, if God peradventure may give them repentance, to the acknowledging of the truth: <hi>Of which counſel, ſuch fierceneſs as hath appeared in the Diſputation of Divines, down from before the Council of</hi> Nice <hi>to this preſent time, is a Violation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
